<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The moderate Trinitarian containing a description of the Holy Trinity, both according to Scripture, and approved authors for learning, and adherence to the Trinitarian doctrine : being an argument shewing that moderation may and ought to be shewn by and to persons of different conceptions concerning some circumstances relating to the knowledg of the Holy Trinity : together with a short reply to Mr. Joseph Taylor's Brief inquiry whether those who own, and those who deny the divinity of Christ, may communicate together / by Daniel Allen.</title>
            <author>Allen, Daniel, fl. 1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 181 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A23631</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A1023</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17226</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13037290</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13037290</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96824</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A23631)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96824)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 405:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The moderate Trinitarian containing a description of the Holy Trinity, both according to Scripture, and approved authors for learning, and adherence to the Trinitarian doctrine : being an argument shewing that moderation may and ought to be shewn by and to persons of different conceptions concerning some circumstances relating to the knowledg of the Holy Trinity : together with a short reply to Mr. Joseph Taylor's Brief inquiry whether those who own, and those who deny the divinity of Christ, may communicate together / by Daniel Allen.</title>
                  <author>Allen, Daniel, fl. 1699.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>vi, 7-46 [i.e. 44] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Mary Fabian ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Two columns to the page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Taylor, Joseph, 17th/18th cent. --  Brief inquiry whether they who assert ... the divinity of our Lord Jesus, may have communion together.</term>
               <term>Trinity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96824:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96824:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Moderate Trinitarian: CONTAINING A DESCRIPTION OF THE Holy Trinity, Both according to Scripture, and approved Authors for Learning, and Adherence to the Trinitarian Doctrine.</p>
            <p>BEING An Argument ſhewing that <hi>Moderation</hi> may and ought to be ſhewn by and to Perſons of different Conceptions concerning ſome Circumſtances relating to the Knowledg of the Holy Trinity.</p>
            <p>Together with a ſhort Reply to Mr. <hi>Joſeph Taylor</hi>'s brief Inquiry whether thoſe who own, and thoſe who deny the Divinity of Chriſt, may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate together.</p>
            <p>By DANIEL ALLEN.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Bleſſed are the Peace-makers.</l>
               <l>But mark ſuch as cauſe Diviſions, and avoid them.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Mary Fabian</hi> at <hi>Mercers Chappel</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:96824:2"/>
            <pb n="iii" facs="tcp:96824:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>IT was not any Ambition in me (I'll aſſure thee) to teach my worthy Brethren, of far greater Parts and Indowments than my ſelf, that induced me thus publickly to appear with the enſuing Tract: But it was the hideous noiſe that the rending and tearing of Churches made, that rouſed me up, and provoked me thus publickly to expoſe my ſelf to the cenſure of many, when I might have ſlept ſecurely in a whole Skin, with my Sentiments lockt up in my own Breaſt.</p>
            <p>But I ſaw: What did I ſee? Why I thought I ſaw the ſparks of miſguided and intemperate Zeal in divers well meaning Men, to ſet ſome Churches in a Flame; which like the dreadful Conflagration in <hi>London,</hi> burnt down to the ground many famous (tho not Pariſh) Churches. All that have appeared in print about this Subject, ſo far as I obſerved, have cried out Peace and Truth: yet notwithſtanding, to my diſcerning, have filled their Buckets with Oil, and threw them into the Flame. How that could quench it judg you: Nay, thought I, if all your printing be in that faſhion, the Fire will never be quenched. So I got my Bucket, as I truſt, full of Cordial Water, and away come I to the Preſs. I thought, if I could be but inſtrumental to quench and ſave one Poſt or Beam of the Church, my labour would not be loſt; and I ſhall do more good than they that adminiſter Oil.</p>
            <p>Beſides, I conſidered that thoſe little Books, or Buckets of Oil, were very fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent: every year, or half year, out comes a Piece crying, <hi>Hereſy! Hereſy!</hi> But not one comes like the Dove, with the Olive Branch of Peace in their Mouths; neither was there one Word tending that way in any of their Writings: and hereby many young Converts, as well as others, were much puzled, and made to
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:96824:3"/> doubt. Wherefore I thought if ſomething were ſaid publickly to demonſtrate that there may be a ſafe Medium and Correſpondence found out and maintain'd betwixt the two Parties, it might be acceptable to the Doubtful; and through the Bleſſing of God might become ſucceſsful to help the tender Conſcience.</p>
            <p>There be ſome ſo confident and ſettled, that I have no hopes of them: but then I conſider there be many have not renounced their Reaſon, and therefore will hear Reaſon; to ſuch I ſpeak. I know ſome will throw away my Writing as Dirt, while others will condemn it e're they hear it: yet as God hath heretofore bleſſed my poor Endeavours and Diſcourſes of this kind with ſucceſs, ſo I truſt theſe my Labours will not be in vain.</p>
            <p>Neither can I expect to want Readers, ſince there be ſome, and not a few, who know me, and of them not a few that love me; and they will read me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they love me. And there be ſome, and not a few, that do not love me, nor the Deſign I here purſue; and they'l read me to ſee what they can pick up againſt me. And there be ſome, and not a few, that are ſtagger'd in their own Minds, and they'l read me for their own ſatisfaction, becauſe they long to hear what can be ſaid for Moderation.</p>
            <p>Moreover, I was induced to take this Courſe, partly becauſe a Book will come to ſpeak where I cannot, and poſſibly when I cannot: partly becauſe in argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this caſe, I find that too commonly there are apt to be Heats and Paſſions, which commonly prevent perſons conſidering what is ſaid, and the Arguments are many times cut off by the Buttocks, and ſo condemned, becauſe not well un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood. I have ſeen ſome Men about theſe things ſo eagerly contending, that Heat hath blinded them; and like Men tied back to back, tho they were cloſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, yet they could not ſee one another.</p>
            <p>But now having my Book in their hand, they may deliberatly conſider all my Arguments to the end, without thoſe Moleſtations which often happen in Debates. And if any man fall into a paſſion with my Papers, when my Perſon is not preſent, if I hear of it, I ſhall think him to be (as ſome of them are ſaid to be in the Tribe of <hi>Dan</hi>) an angry Fellow.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Kind Reader,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I tread in a Path heretofore untrod by any that I know of: for tho many worthy men are for Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity notwithſtanding the preſent Controverſy; yet none that I know of, have publickly appeared to vindicate ſuch a Practice. And I wiſh this my Attempt may be a means to provoke ſome more ſublime Genius than mine, to poliſh and perfect that which is here rough-drawn. However, ſince I lead the Van ſo far as I know, in ſo troubleſome, toilſome, and difficult a Path, between thoſe Extreams which have in many Ages puzled the moſt Learned Men; if I ſhould appear to ſtumble, and ſometimes to trip and reel,
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:96824:3"/> I hope thy Candor will accept of my well-meaning, and rather pity than cenſure me: and then thou acteſt like a Chriſtian. And as I profeſs not my ſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible, and therefore ſubject to err; and eſpecially in ſo untrodden a Path: If any will Chriſtian-like, inform me wherein I am wanting, I ſhall eſteem him among the number of my ſpecial Friends. In ſhort, however I may have cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantially erred, tho I know it not, yet in the main I meant well; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore well-meaning men will take it well. I would, if I could, perſwade every one to be a Healer of the Breach: the unpleaſant ſound of Diſcord hath too long afflicted our Ears, and diſturbed our Heads. What pity is it we ſhould ſo run upon a Party, when amongst our ſelves there is hardly any conſiderable Society that can be found: the Matter is ſo dark, and ſo variouſly underſtood, that we that profeſs to be moſt Orthodox, are ſadly divided and ſubdivided in our thoughts, if a ſtrict ſcrutiny ſhould be made into our Sentiments about it.</p>
                  <p>That Party of Brethren which I have in this enſuing Treatiſe mainly and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially endeavoured to vindicate, and to propoſe a Medium with, are thoſe which ſeveral of my Brethren met in <hi>Goſwel-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>London</hi> in the years <hi>1693,</hi> and <hi>1696.</hi> did in a printed Paper publickly proteſt againſt, and withdraw from. As for my Brethren of <hi>Socinus</hi>'s Perſwaſion concerning Chriſt, ſo far as I know their Principles, I am very oppoſite to them in my own Thoughts, yet have I Charity for them. But having but little converſe with them, I conceive I am ignorant of many Points they hold; and therefore I could not ſo directly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude them in what I have ſaid for Moderation: nevertheleſs I ſuppoſe many things that I have wrote, do tend to demonſtrate that Chriſtian Charity and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion may and ought to be ſhewn to them all, tho, as aforeſaid, I could not through Ignorance ſo directly ſpeak to every point of their caſe; and I would adviſe all my Brethren to be wary how they ſeparate from them only on the account of that Principle: The dreadful conſequences of Diviſion at all times, but eſpecially at this time of day, ought to make all Chriſtians wary how they raſhly adhere to, or abet ſuch a Practice. <hi>Bleſſed are the Peace-makers: but mark ſuch as cauſe Diviſions amongſt you, and avoid them.</hi> And I would adviſe all Churches diligently to inſtil Arguments for Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity in all their Members, but in their young men more eſpecially: for of many Evils that I have ſeen, this is none of the leaſt, namely, when a young man comes to be uſeful in the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Work of the Church, and in all appearance is like to prove a hopeful and very uſeful young man; but by and by ſome fiery Spirit, heated with Zeal in this Contr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy, comes, <hi>Jehu</hi> like, and lays before him the eminent Danger he is in, if he abet or communicate with ſuch and ſuch perſons; for, ſays be, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y deny the true Chriſt; and then the uſual Arguments in this caſe are urged. The unwary and unexperienced young man ſwallows all down, and it preſently appears in him: for 'tis commonly ſeen to be ſo, if there were ſomething within encouraging in
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:96824:4"/> this caſe. I know what I ſpeak by experience. As I ſaid, this ſoon appears in his Diſcourſes and Sermons; 'tis well if he can preach one Sermon without it, or forbear making it the Subject of whole Sermons. And this being a new thing, the People are many of them amuſed, and their heads filled, and more neceſſary Truths neglected: and the young men eſpecially have commonly their heads as full of it as an Egg is of Meat. The conſequence commonly is the breach of the Peace of the Church. I would adviſe alſo all young men to walk in thoſe Paths warily and ſoftly, and beg the aſſiſtance of Grace to guide them in the right way; to behave themſelves humbly, and be exceeding tender of the Peace of the Church they belong to; and well to conſider, that Peace is much ſooner broke than repaired.</p>
                  <p>If my Labours may prove uſeful, to ſhew any how far the contending Parties are agreed in the fundamental Points of Faith in God and Chriſt, and may conduce to the Peace of Chriſtians, I ſhall have my end: So reſts</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Thine to ſerve thee in what I may, Daniel Allen.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:96824:4"/>
            <div type="introduction">
               <head>INTRODUCTION.</head>
               <div type="proposition">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Propoſition.</hi> That Moderation may and ought to be ſhewn by, and to Perſons of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Apprehenſions about ſome Circumſtances relating to the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg and Definition of the Holy Trinity.</head>
                  <p>BY Moderation I mean Chriſtian Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Communion; and what Perſons I directly intend, hath been mentioned in my Epiſtle to the Reader, and what Circumſtances I intend, will more plainly appear in the Sequel of my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>A general Argument to prove the Propoſition.</head>
                  <p>BEcauſe the Perſons here intended do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and differ not in their Opinion from their Brethren in any eſſential point ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary to Salvation, whether a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Object of Worſhip, or manner of paying our Chriſtian Obedience to him; I take it for granted, that it will not be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted that perſons ſo qualified as here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, are fit Subjects for Chriſtian Charity and Communion: But the great work will be to prove the Minor, <hi>viz.</hi> That thoſe Perſons are ſuch as agree, and differ not in the things aforeſaid. And to demonſtrate this ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed difficult Caſe, I ſhall give a Definition of the Holy Trinity in the order and manner as followeth: <hi>viz.</hi> firſt, Of the moſt High God: Secondly, Of the Chriſt of God: Thirdly, Of the Spirit of God. And I ſhall deſcribe them according to Scripture-Revelation, and the explanation of approved Authors both for Learning, Parts, and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence to the Athanaſian Belief, both antient and modern; that ſo thereby I may ſhew both where the difference is not, and where it is; that a Judgment thereon may the eaſier be made. And for the more clear and diſtinct underſtanding of the matter, I ſhall handle my Diſcourſe concerning each of theſe three apart. And firſt concerning the <hi>moſt High God.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:96824:5"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the moſt High God.</head>
               <p>THis Chapter I ſhall divide into three Sections: Firſt, of the means where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by God is known to Men: Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, what God moſt High is: Thirdly, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the manner of paying Adoration and Worſhip to him.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. I.</hi> Of the Means by which God is known to Men.</head>
                  <p>THE Means to know God are twofold; firſt, External: Secondly, Internal.</p>
                  <p>The External Means are the five Senſes, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming the Judgment and Underſtanding, by and from the Works and Word of God: for there is no rational Man, but hears, ſees, taſtes, ſmells, and feels, ſufficiently to inform and convince him that there is a God, (yea a great and glorious one, the firſt Cauſe of all things.)</p>
                  <p n="1">1. From his Works. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.19, 20. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that which may be known of God is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in them: for the inviſible things of him from the Creation of the World are clearly ſeen, being underſtood by the things that are made, even his eternal Power and Godhead.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But 2. The Imprint of God's Image on the Creature (even the wonderful Power, Wiſdom and Skill which he hath ſhewed in forming it, and providing for it) whereby our Underſtanding is informed of him through the five Senſes, is but a rough Draught of his Shadow, in compariſon of the more ample Diſcove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y we have of him in his Word; by which further and clearer Diſcovery our Underſtanding are informed through the Senſes of hearing it, and ſeeing it to read it.</p>
                  <p>All this Knowledg attained by means of our Senſes is e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rnal or outward; and tho neceſſary, yet is not of it ſelf a ſaving Knowledg of God, but h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th its Reſidence in the Hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>That it is neceſſary is evident: for if we do not know there is a God, or know the true God by ſome infallible Demonſtrations, we can never regularly, no nor indeed at all, ſerve God, except blindly, like the <hi>Athenians,</hi> who worſhipped they knew not what (or the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nknown God:</hi>) And tho we may all in ſome ſenſe ſay ſo of our ſelves, in as much as none can find out the Almighty to perfection; yet of ſuch a Knowledg of God as in and by his Word and Works he ordinarily diſcovers of himſelf, we ought not to be ignorant: which what it is, and what it is not, ſhall be my endeavours anon to ſhew. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, that this Knowledg alone is not ſaving, appears, becauſe thouſands there be who have and can diſcourſe very well of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Atheiſtical Notions, who yet never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs remain deſtitute of true ſaving Faith and Communion with him: therefore altho the external Knowledg of God be good, yea a neceſſary thing in its place; yet it is not ſaving, except ſanctified and joined with the internal Knowledg of God.</p>
                  <p>Which is the ſecond thing, or kind of Knowledg I am to ſpeak to; and that is that mentioned and intended Mat. 11.27. <hi>All things are delivered to me of my Father; and no man knoweth the Son but the Father; neither knoweth any man the Father ſave the Son, and he to whomſoever the Son will reveal him.</hi> This Knowledg properly dwells in the Heart, and is attained by the Exerciſe of ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:96824:5"/> Faith wrought by the Spirit of Chriſt; it flows from an inward ſpiritual Communion the Soul hath with God, through the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator, by which the humble Soul ſees the Almighty paſſing by, blotting out, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning its Sins, and ready and willing to pour into its Boſom all neceſſary good things of all kinds; from whence are nouriſhed Hope, Peace, Joy, and Love.</p>
                  <p>This Knowledg is ſaving, and it is as ſoon attained by Perſons of weak and mean Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that ſincerely ſeek it, as by any what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, as appears in <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.25. where Chriſt <hi>thanks his Father in that he had hid thoſe things from the Wiſe and Prudent, and had revealed them unto Babes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. II.</hi> Concerning God moſt High, what he is.</head>
                  <p>IN this Section you have a Deſcription of God moſt High, reſpecting his Eſſence, Being, or Subſtance, and his Eſſential Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties: and firſt, in the Negative; Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Affirmative: and that firſt, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to plain Texes of Scripture; ſecondly, according to ſeveral Authors. In which Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe are included theſe following uſeful Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, How far the contending Parties are agreed. Secondly, wherein they differ; the Caſe and the Controverſy betwixt them fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly propounded, examined, opened, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained. In which are theſe things following <hi>obſervable.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. That thoſe things concerning the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the moſt High, wherein they are agreed, are very <hi>plain</hi> from Scripture and Reaſon; but the controverſal pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t very <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure,</hi> not only to Reaſon and the Unlearned, but alſo to the Underſtandings of the moſt Profound and Learned.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That the things wherein they are agreed are plainly in words at length declared, both in the Old and New Teſtament, as matters to be owned and believed; and <hi>therefore</hi> abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary to Salvation; But the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſal; part is not preſſed as a thing to be underſtood, or neceſſary to be believed by the Worſhippers of this God: In the Old Teſtament hardly any Footſteps of it appear; and 'tis aſſerted only by and from conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from the new Teſtament.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That both Orthodox and Hereticks (ſo called) are agreed in all the Eſſentials and neceſſary parts of Truth, reſpecting the Knowledg of the moſt High God, harmoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and unanimouſly owning and teaching the ſame things of his Eſſence and eſſential Properties: The Hereticks (ſo eſteemed) owning and worſhipping <hi>the ſame God, and no other,</hi> that made Heaven and Earth, and appeared to <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 17.1. not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying but firmly owning <hi>all and whole, and every part of the ſame Eſſence, and all and every eſſential Property thereof,</hi> according as the above-named Orthodox do.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That the great Controverſy and Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence concerning God betwixt the above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Parties is not eſſential, but only circumſtantial, <hi>viz.</hi> about the manner or Mode of its. ſubſiſting, and not about the Divine Eſſence it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>As touching the Knowledg of God, I ſhall treat firſt negatively: He is not any graven Image, or Device of Man's Hands, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.29. nor no Man; becauſe Man is mortal, but God cedureth for ever, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 136.13. nor no Angel; firſt, becauſe they are made; ſecondly, are Meſſengers, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.7, 14. But he is without beginning, and above all, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not created nor ſent.</p>
                  <p>But Secondly, In the affirmative, God is a Spirit or Spiritual Subſtance, <hi>John</hi> 4.24. Not a created Spirit, as the Angels; but an infinite, independent, intire, inviſible Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; the firſt Cauſe of, and ſoveraign <hi>high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt</hi> Power over all things: Infinite, incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible, unſearchable in Glory, in Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, in Strength, in Wiſdom, in Knowledg, in Juſtice, in Love, in Mercy, in Bounty, in Goodneſs, in Purity, in Compaſſion, in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96824:6"/> in Truth and Perfection.</p>
                  <p>Theſe are the eſſential and inſeparable Properties of the Divine Eſſence or Being of God moſt High, <hi>the immediate Object of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There may be, and Scripture ſhews there are ſome who in a ſubordinate manner bear the name of God, becauſe he allows it them as ruling from and under him; and therefore as Viceroys or chief Magiſtrates under God in their places, they bear, tho leſs properly, the name of God (to give an inſtance or two in the room of many) of this kind or ſort are Angels, of whom <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.15. where he ſaith, <hi>There he that are called Gods in Heaven;</hi> who ſurely could not be falſe Gods, for they could not get to Heaven; therefore Angels through the Excellency of their work obtain that honourable Name; and ſo do men, <hi>John</hi> 10.35. But to paſs this; only he that hath th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe eſſential Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, is God <hi>moſt High:</hi> on which Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties I'll inlarge a little. If he be invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, then it is not ſafe for me to form any ſhape of him in my Apprehenſions, any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than a Glorious, unwordable Being. If he be independent, then he ſtays only on himſelf, and all things ſtay on him. If he be infinite in Power and Perfection, <hi>then he is a ſingle uncompounded Eſſence, only one in Number and Being:</hi> For it is morally impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that there ſhould be two <hi>infinite Beings;</hi> for if one be infinite, the other cannot: and it is alike impoſſible that there ſhould be two <hi>moſt Highs;</hi> for if they are equal, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them both can ſay that he is the <hi>moſt</hi> High, becauſe there is another as high as he. Alſo it alike argues Imperfection; for if one Moſt High be ſufficient, then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is needleſs; and where there is more than needs, it is <hi>Imperfection.</hi> Again, if one moſt High of himſelf be not ſufficient with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out another, that argues <hi>Imperfection.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they that worſhip the true and moſt High God, muſt and ought to conceive of him as a <hi>ſingle</hi> impartible Being or Eſſence; <hi>one</hi> in Power, in Will, in Thought, in Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, and in all things belonging to his <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</hi> And ſo hath God directed us to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of him in his Word; <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.4. <hi>Hear, O Iſrael, the Lord thy God is one Lord.</hi> Iſa. 44.6. <hi>Beſides me there is no God.</hi> Mark 12.32. <hi>There is one God, and there is none other but he.</hi> 1 Cor. 8.6. <hi>But to us there is but One God: There is none other God but one.</hi> Epheſ. 4.6. <hi>There is One God and Father of all, who is above all.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus far am I come ſafely, no body hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing to contradict or gainſay: (that is, no body that owns the <hi>true God</hi>) But on all hands we are agreed about the Eternal Eſſence and Divine Properties.</p>
                  <p>Theſe things as undeniable, all Chriſtian Men believe, the Scripture proves, and God's Works manifeſt. This Deſcription is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for me to underſtand, in order to direct me how to place and exerciſe my Faith in God aright, how to pay my Duties and Worſhip to him, and conſequently <hi>to my Salvation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But now I am arrived at the Borders of the Controverſy betwixt the <hi>Trinitarians</hi> and the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> the <hi>Athanaſians</hi> and nick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam'd <hi>Arians.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But to paſs my Task, 'tis requiſite to give yet a further Deſcription of this <hi>One moſt High God;</hi> which following Deſcription is ſaid to be drawn from Scripture conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, but is much more plainly ſet down in words at length in other Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. I ſhall firſt cite the Athanaſian Creed on this Subject: <q rend="margSglQuotes">The Catholick Faith is this, That we worſhip one God in Trinity, and Trinity in Unity; neither confounding the Perſons nor dividing the Subſtance.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Nicene Creed ſays thus: <q rend="margSglQuotes">I believe in One God the Father, Maker of Heaven and Earth, and of all things viſible and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible; and in one Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the only begotten Son of God; begotten of the Father before all Worlds; God of God, Light of Light; very God of very God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten not made; of one Subſtance with the Father, by whom all things were made: And in the Holy Spirit, the quickening Spirit, who proceeds from the Father and the Son, and in like manner is adored and glorified with the Father and the Son, and who ſpake by the Prophets.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:96824:6"/>3. Next I ſhall cite the firſt of the 39 Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> 
                     <q rend="margSglQuotes">There is but <hi>One</hi> living and true God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and in Unity of this Godhead there be three Perſons, of one Subſtance, Power and Eternity.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. Next I ſhall cite Mr. <hi>Joſeph Wright</hi> in his Book intitul'd, <hi>Brief Animadverſions on five Articles,</hi> pag. 2. <q rend="margSglQuotes">So that we did then, and do hold that there is <hi>One only true and living God,</hi> the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit, all three of the very ſame Divine Nature and Being.</q> And in the ſame Book, pag. 3. lin. 28. <q rend="margSglQuotes">When we ſay theſe three are one, we did, and now believe that the Father, Word (or Son) and Holy Spirit, are all three of the ſame Divine Nature and Being from ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting to everlaſting, the Creator and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor of all things, <hi>One</hi> only true and living God, in three diſtinct and <hi>undivided</hi> Divine Perſons: Thus far Mr. <hi>Wright.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. Next I ſhall cite Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> in his Book intituled, <hi>The Doctrine of the Trinity vindicat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> printed <hi>An.</hi> 1669, pag. 29. <q rend="margSglQuotes">In the Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of this Doctrine unto the edification of the Church, there is contained a further explanation of the things before aſſerted, as propoſed, directed, and in themſelves the Object of our Faith; namely, how God is one in reſpect of Nature, Subſtance, Eſſence, Godhead, or Divine Being: How being Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, he ſubſiſteth in theſe three diſtinct Perſons. And <hi>Pag.</hi> 112. The diſtinction which the Scripture reveals between Father, Son and Holy Spirit, is that whereby they are three Perſons diſtinctly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in the <hi>ſame</hi> Divine Eſſence or Being. Now a Divine Perſon is nothing elſe, but a Divine Perſon upon the account of an eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Property ſubſiſting in an eſpecial man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: as in the Perſon of the Father there is the Divine Eſſence or Being, with its Property of begetting the Son, ſubſiſting in an eſpecial manner in the Father; and becauſe this Perſon hath the <hi>whole</hi> Divine Nature, all the eſſential Properties of that Nature are in that Perſon. <hi>Page</hi> 122. See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing here that the name of God ſupplies the place of a Species, tho it be ſingular abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely, as it reſpects the Divine Nature, which is <hi>abſolutely ſingular</hi> and <hi>One,</hi> and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be <hi>multiplied;</hi> yet in reſpect of commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication it is otherwiſe, it is communicated unto more.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. I ſhall cite next Mr. <hi>John Preſton</hi> in his Book intitul'd, <hi>Life eternal, or a Treatiſe of the Knowledg of the Divine Eſſence,</hi> fourth Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, printed 1034, page 48, 49. <q rend="margSglQuotes">If there be <hi>two things</hi> in God, then there is <hi>Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication:</hi> now all Multiplication ariſeth from ſome Imperfection, from ſome want and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: for if <hi>one</hi> would ſerve, <hi>two</hi> would be needleſs; if one Medicine would cure, two would be unneceſſary; <hi>ſo in all things elſe.</hi> So that the reaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n of Multiplication is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>one</hi> will not ſerve the turn: Therefore God being all-ſufficient, it is not needful, yea it <hi>cannot</hi> be, that a breaking in <hi>two</hi> ſhould be admitted in him, and conſequently he muſt be <hi>moſt ſimple,</hi> without all <hi>compoſition,</hi> a pure and entire Eſſence, full of himſelf, and nothing beſides. And a little further thus: Whereſoever there is any compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, there muſt be two or three things; ſo that there may be a Diviſion; they are ſeparable, tho not ſeparated: But where Diviſion is, there may be a Diſſolution, and ſo Deſtruction, though it never be. But of God we cannot ſay that this may be, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently there cannot be <hi>two</hi> things in him: but what he is, he is <hi>One</hi> moſt ſimple, moſt pure, and moſt entire Being, without all <hi>Compoſition and Multiplication.</hi> If God be not ſimple, there muſt be parts of which he is compounded; but in God bleſſed for ever there are no <hi>parts,</hi> becauſe then there ſhould be Imperfection, for every <hi>part</hi> is imperfect.</q> I ſhall cite one Author more, and then make ſome uſe of the whole.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Mr. <hi>Thomas Monk</hi> in his <hi>notable</hi> Book of the Trinity, intituled, <hi>A Cure for the canker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Error,</hi> Pag. 55. has theſe words: <q rend="margSglQuotes">Not to the end it ſhould make a Multitude of Gods, or <hi>divide</hi> the Eſſence, but to diſtinguiſh the Perſons, becauſe tho there be one Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Father, another Perſon of the Son, and another of the Holy Ghoſt, yet the Father is not another thing, or another God diſtinct from the Son and the Holy Ghoſt; neither is the Son another thing, or another God diſtinct from the Father and the Holy Ghoſt; neither is the Holy Ghoſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96824:7"/> another thing, or another God diſtinct from the Father and the Son; becauſe the Nature of God is but <hi>one</hi> and indiviſible; although the Father be one, the Son another, and the Holy Ghoſt another: and therefore they are not of divers natures, of another and <hi>divers</hi> Subſtance, not conjoined or knit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in one Subſtance (as Men which have one common Eſſence) not only of the <hi>like</hi> Subſtance, but of <hi>one</hi> and the ſame Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; have the ſame Eſſence, the ſame Eternity, the ſame Will, the ſame Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And <hi>page</hi> 57. '<hi>Qu.</hi> Be there any parts or kinds in God? Anſw. <hi>None at all,</hi> becauſe he is a moſt <hi>ſimple</hi> Eſſence; which doth admit no <hi>Compoſition or Diviſion,</hi> and ſimply and in every reſpect of Unity <hi>one.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Having given you this Deſcription of the Moſt High God, both from the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and thoſe Authors; I ſhall now come to make that uſe of it, which at firſt I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed and intended; and that is, to ſhew, that there is no <hi>eſſential,</hi> but only a <hi>circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial</hi> difference in the Apprehenſions of the Parties before named, concerning the Moſt High God, and the Deſcription here given of Him. Only note, that that which concerns the difference about the Son and Holy Ghoſt, will be here ſpoken unto but occaſionally and in ſhort, becauſe I ſhall treat more largely, diſtinctly, and directly of them in their proper place: Whereas I am now preciſely treating of the <hi>Moſt High God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But to the end that a plain Diſcovery of the Difference concerning the Moſt High (which hath made ſuch a Noiſe and Confuſion in the World in many Ages, and in our times) may appear, I ſhall ſtate the Sum of the caſe in this one ſhort Queſtion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whether the most Glorious, Eternal, Intire, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncompounded, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndivided, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndividable Eſſence of the one Moſt High God, do (at the ſame time, and at all times from Eternity to Eternity) ſubſiſt</hi> all and whole <hi>both in</hi> one <hi>Perſon, and alſo in like m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nner in</hi> three <hi>Perſons, or all, and whole only in</hi> one <hi>Perſon?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Our dividing Brethren are for the firſt part of this Queſtion, and our accu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d Brethren are for the latter part thereof.</p>
                  <p>That this is the Sum of the Difference, and that this Diff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rence is only Ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cumſtantial, is now my buſineſs to make appear; which I ſhall endeavour to do, partly from the former Deſcription and Quotations, partly from the natural force of <hi>our</hi> Opinions, and partly from further Quotations.</p>
                  <p>But in the firſt place, give me leave to treat a little in the Negative. Let us firſt obſerve where the difference is <hi>not:</hi> The Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion controverted is not whether or no any of the Idols of <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, or any of the Multitude of the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Gods, or antient Heathen Deities formerly worſhipped by them, or the falſe Deities worſhipped by Infidels in foreign Parts now; I ſay, the Queſtion is not whether any of theſe be the true God or no. Neither is the Queſtion whether the glorious Eſſence or Godhead, which the Scripture ſays is in Heaven, whether He alone, and <hi>only</hi> He, be the Moſt High God, and that we ought to pay our duty to none but Him, and ſuch as He ſhall <hi>delegate under him:</hi> for theſe things are owned on all hands. Neither is it at all queſtioned on either hand whether there be above <hi>one</hi> Moſt High God, or whether his Eſſence be infinite, eternal, independent, all Wiſdom, Power, Greatneſs, Holineſs, Juſtice, Love, Mercy, Knowledg, Bounty, Goodneſs, Truth, Perfection. Nay, in <hi>all</hi> the Eſſential Properties of the Divine Nature which Holy Scripture and Reaſon do teach, there is ſtill a joint Conſent and Agreement on all hands. Where then is the difference, as to cauſe ſo loud a noiſe of <hi>Hereſy! Hereſy!</hi> theſe Men deny the Foundation of all Chriſtian Religion and Worſhip; nay deny the true God!</p>
                  <p>Why let us conſider a little, ſince there is an agreement about, and in all the eſſential Properties of the true God, and an Agreement <hi>which</hi> Eſſence is the true God. Is there any known material difference about the Eſſence it ſelf? the matter of it let us examine.</p>
                  <p>No, we find none here neither: for that it is an intire, uncompounded, impartible, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividable, <hi>one Substance,</hi> or Eſſence, thoſe ſuppoſed Hereticks ſay, and ſo <hi>ſay</hi> we. Let us look over the Quotations already cited: Firſt, ſays <hi>Athanaſius</hi>'s Creed, <hi>not dividing the Subſtance.</hi> 2. The Nicene Creed ſays, <hi>One Subſtance.</hi> 3. The firſt of the 39 Articles ſays, <hi>one living and true God,</hi> without Body, <hi>Parts</hi> or Paſſions, of <hi>One</hi> Subſtance. 4. Mr.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:96824:7"/> 
                     <hi>Wright</hi> ſays, that all three are in the <hi>ſame</hi> Divine Nature, and being in three diſtinct and <hi>undivided</hi> Divine Perſons; and on that account grants that the Father is the <hi>only</hi> true God. 5. Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> ſays, God is <hi>One</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his Nature, Subſtance, Eſſence, Godhead, or Divine Being: and further ſays, that the name of God is a ſingular <hi>abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely,</hi> as it reſpects the Divine Nature; which is abſolutely ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ngular and <hi>One,</hi> and cannot be <hi>multiplied.</hi> 6. Mr. <hi>Preſton</hi> ſays that God being <hi>Allſufficient,</hi> it is not needful, yea it cannot be that a breaking in <hi>two</hi> ſhould be admitted in him, and conſequently he muſt be moſt <hi>ſimple</hi> without all <hi>compoſition,</hi> a pure and intire Eſſence, full of himſelf and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing beſides: And a little further ſays, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently there cannot be two things in him, but what he is he is <hi>One</hi> moſt ſimple, moſt pure, and moſt intire being, without all Compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Multiplication: and further he ſays there are no parts in him. Laſtly, Mr. <hi>Monk</hi> ſays, That the Perſons, tho diſtinct amongſt themſelves, yet are not differing things one from another, becauſe the nature of God is but <hi>One</hi> and indiviſible; and further ſays, they are not conjoined or knit together in one Subſtance, as Men which have one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Eſſence: They are not only of the <hi>like</hi> Subſtance, but of <hi>one and the ſame Subſtance, have the ſame Eſſence,</hi> &amp;c. And in anſwer to the Queſtion, Are there any <hi>Parts</hi> or Kinds in God? anſwers, none at all; becauſe he is a moſt ſimple Eſſence, which doth admit of no <hi>Compoſition or Diviſion,</hi> and ſimple, and in every reſpect of Unity <hi>One.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus you ſee, having ſummed up the Evidence, as ſays the Foreman, ſo they ſay all, they are all agreed in their Verdict; both Orthodox, and Hereticks (ſo called) are thus far in all reſpects jointly and fully a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eed as with one Voice, to publiſh that their apprehenſion of the one true God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting his Eſſence, is an <hi>undivided, undi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidable,</hi> intirely <hi>one Subſtance,</hi> not ſubſiſting or poſſible to be ſubſiſting in parts, or hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any <hi>Parts</hi> in him. And ſo ſays the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, God is <hi>a Spirit,</hi> not <hi>Spirits.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And indeed this Doctrine of the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of the Divine Eſſence we muſt maintain, or elſe we do nothing: for if once we admit of ſeveral parts in that Eſſence, we may as well admit (and there ſeems a neceſſity that it ſhould be) ſo many <hi>ſeveral Spirits,</hi> and indeed ſo many <hi>Moſt High Gods;</hi> which can be called one only by conſent and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or at moſt one in kind.</p>
                  <p>But the Doctrine of Plurality of Gods <hi>moſt High</hi> is repugnant to Reaſon, refuted by Scripture, and abhorred by Mahometans.</p>
                  <p>Beſides, if you divide <hi>Eſſence</hi> in your thoughts, then you muſt divide the <hi>Eſſential Properties,</hi> ſuch as Mercy, Juſtice, Wiſdom, Bounty, and the reſt; I ſay, you muſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide them into as many parts as you divide the Eſſence in your thoughts: As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample: Suppoſe you divide it into three parts; then you muſt ſuppoſe in your mind three Attributes of Juſtice, three of Mercy, three of Wiſdom, and ſo of all the reſt; or elſe you muſt imagine ſome of the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes in one part, and ſome in another: as thus, Juſtice and Power in one, Mercy and Wiſdom in another, Truth and Bounty in another, and ſo of the reſt: or elſe you muſt imagine that ſome of the parts have none of the Attributes, and that will be <hi>Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy and N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nſenſe;</hi> ſince I think all will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that nothing can be <hi>eſſentially</hi> God moſt High, but that which is or hath all the Divine Eſſential Properties. And ſo go which way to work you will, if you admit of <hi>Parts,</hi> you confound the <hi>Subſtance,</hi> as <hi>Athanaſius</hi> ſays. But enough of this. We are unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly agreed in the Unity and Undivided<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Divine Eſſence. Well, thus far are we come, looking for the difference, but finding none. Why where is it? What is become of it? that great difference that hath troubled the World and Church ſo many hundred years, and ſet good men together by the ears To<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th and Nail, occaſion'd a great Volume of hard, bitter, ſharp, biting Words againſt each other? and yet you ſee we are all agreed about the main Matter, Subſtance, or Eſſence of the moſt High; nay and in all the eſſential Properties of him too: And yet can there be any material dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference about him notwithſtanding? that's ſtrange! how can this thing be?</p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:96824:8"/>
                  <p>Why yes, yet there is a difference: but whether a material one or no, muſt be left to my conſidering Reader to judg. It is not whether this Divine undivided Eſſence, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout which, and all its eſſential Properties, we are <hi>fully</hi> agreed; whether, I ſay, it ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in one Divine Perſon: For this is alſo <hi>jointly</hi> agreed on all hands, as I ſhall preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew: But it is this, Whether it ſubſiſt <hi>only in One</hi> Divine Perſon, or <hi>both in One,</hi> and alſo in like manner in <hi>Three.</hi> The Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox is for the latter, the Heretick affirms the former.</p>
                  <p>Thus near are we come, and I doubt not anon to ſhew you that we are yet nearer than all this. But firſt I'll demonſtrate this: tho firſt of all we muſt treat of the word <hi>Perſon,</hi> what in this Controverſy is underſtood by it: And becauſe I am a little at a loſs to explain the thing, I will therefore give you Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> and Mr. <hi>Monk</hi>'s Deſcription. Firſt, Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> if you look back to the firſt Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of him: <q rend="margSglQuotes">Now (ſays he) a Divine Perſon is nothing elſe but a Divine Perſon upon the account of an eſpecial Property of <hi>ſubſiſting</hi> in an eſpecial manner.</q> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Dr. <hi>Hall,</hi> as I find him quoted by Mr. <hi>Monk,</hi> Page 46. of his <hi>Cure for the cankering Error,</hi> hath theſe Words: <q rend="margSglQuotes">We may think here of <hi>one</hi> Subſtance in <hi>three Subſiſtences, one Eſſence</hi> in <hi>three Relations,</hi> one <hi>Jehovah</hi> begetting, begotten, proceeding, Father, Son, Spirit: yet ſo as the Son is <hi>no other thing</hi> from the Father, but another <hi>Perſon;</hi> or the <hi>Spirit</hi> from the <hi>Son.</hi>
                     </q> Alſo Mr. <hi>Monk,</hi> in his 63 page, propounds this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <q rend="margSglQuotes">How doth the word <hi>Eſſence</hi> differ from the word <hi>Perſon</hi> in God? his anſwer is, Eſſence is the Nature, which is not <hi>more</hi> belonging to one, and <hi>leſs</hi> to another of the three Perſons, but common to them <hi>all,</hi> yea one and the ſame, and cannot be <hi>divided; and is all in each one of them,</hi> not without them, ſubſiſting by it ſelf, to wit, the very Deity it ſelf. And therefore the eſſential Properties which be in them are one in number, of one nature. Now Perſon is the ſubſiſting in the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or the nature of God; which having relation to others, is diſtinguiſhed by ſome incommunicable Properties: for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Perſons are only diſtinguiſhed, not <hi>ſevered:</hi> as indeed three men are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſeparated, tho they be one in kind. The Reaſon is, becauſe the Eſſence of God is infinite and impartible, and therefore it is all in every Perſon, which are not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered one from another, but only diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed amongſt themſelves. But as for the Eſſence of Angels and Men it is finite and partible, ſo that it is not all in every ſingle Perſon, but part in one, and part in another.</q> One Paſſage he hath in page 39. <q rend="margSglQuotes">Fourthly, All the Attributes whether relative, negative, or poſitive, or if any other, in that they proceed from the <hi>Eſſence,</hi> are true of every <hi>Perſon,</hi> becauſe the <hi>whole Eſſence is in every Perſon:</hi> The Father is eternal, the Son is eternal, the Holy Spirit is eternal, becauſe the <hi>whole Eſſence</hi> is in every one of them.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>I need not cite any more, becauſe ſo far as I am able to diſtinguiſh, Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> Dr. <hi>Hall,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Monk</hi> have ſpoken the general ſenſe of all that have writ on this Subject. And now having ſhewed you the Deſcription that theſe men give, if I can tread right in this narrow Path, I will try to give you, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the beſt of my judgment, the ſenſe of what they mean by the word <hi>Perſon</hi> or <hi>Perſons</hi> in the Divine <hi>Eſſence.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt then, I do ſuppoſe by <hi>Perſon</hi> here is not intended a diſtinct ſeparate Being from the <hi>Eſſence,</hi> or from one another; nor yet a diſtinct ſpiritual Subſtance: for this were to divide the Subſtance into three diſtinct divided Perſons. Neither muſt it be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed that Perſon hath a diſtinct Mind or Will from the Eſſence or the other Perſons, for that will neceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rily imply three or four Minds and Wills in the Moſt High, which would be abſurd. Neither muſt the Perſon have any one part of the Divine Eſſence pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to it ſelf, for that would divide the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence into parts, and the Divine Properties alſo, and ſo bring all into confuſion, as hath been ſhewn: therefore <hi>Perſon</hi> muſt be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be ſomething not at all <hi>ſeparated</hi> from any part of the <hi>Eſſence,</hi> or of the other <hi>Perſons:</hi> 
                     <q rend="margSglQuotes">Therefore, ſays Mr. <hi>Monk,</hi> Eſſence
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:96824:8"/> is the nature which is not more belonging to one, and leſs to another of the three Perſons, but common to them all, yea <hi>one and the ſame,</hi> and cannot be <hi>divided,</hi> and is all in each one of them; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore concludes, that the eſſential Properties which be in them are one in number, that is, that the eſſential Property of Love, and the eſſential Property of Mercy, and the eſſential Property of Juſtice, and all the reſt, are <hi>all and whole</hi> in <hi>one</hi> Perſon, and <hi>all and whole</hi> in <hi>another.</hi>
                     </q> And therefore elſewhere ſays, <q rend="margSglQuotes">That all the Attributes (both relative, negative, and poſitive, or any other) of the Divine Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, are true of every Perſon, becauſe the <hi>whole Eſſence</hi> is in every <hi>Perſon.</hi>
                     </q> So that in ſhort the thing is this, that a <hi>Perſon</hi> ſeparate from <hi>Eſſence</hi> is nothing, but is only the <hi>whole</hi> undivided Eſſence, ſubſiſting in a certain <hi>manner or mode;</hi> that is, in one manner in the Father, in another manner or mode in the Son, and in another manner in the Holy Ghoſt: that is, not three diſtinct intelligent <hi>Beings,</hi> but <hi>only one</hi> infinite intire diſtinct intelligent <hi>Being,</hi> ſubſiſting in three undivided inſeparable <hi>Manners or Modes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And this is the general ſenſe, ſo far as I was ever able to diſcern, of all the Authors that ever I read on this Subject.</p>
                  <p>But if this be the Knot of the Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy about the moſt High God, perhaps ſome will ſay it is <hi>dark:</hi> I ſay, perhaps ſo too; very like it may be ſo, elſe what's the matter, think you, that ſo many Men who have long been loving Friends and good Men, yet by this Controverſy have had their Eyes ſo blinded, that they could not ſee one another with an Eye of Charity? And what elſe ſhould be the reaſon that in the Churches where it hath been controverted, there hath oftentimes aroſe ſuch a Miſt and thick Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that many could not ſee their Seats at the Lord's Table? And if any ſhall ask me the meaning of the matter, I muſt anſwer with Mr. <hi>Monk</hi> page 43. That the perfect manner how one perſon is in another is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible and unutterable in this Life.</p>
                  <p>And for my own part, I ſhall much ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther chuſe to <hi>admire</hi> the matter than to illuſtrate my explanation; and I will add with Mr. <hi>Monk</hi> in the aforeſaid page, to be wiſe above what is written, is not Wiſdom, but <hi>perilous</hi> Sin and Folly.</p>
                  <p>And it will not out of my Head, but that it had been much better for every body to have left off at the Deſcription of the moſt High, even there where we on all hands were ſo well agreed, rather than to have run further for a plainer Deſcription till we have almoſt <hi>loſt</hi> our ſelves.</p>
                  <p>And now a word by the way to my B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, who for diſtinction ſake I call of the <hi>Athanaſian Perſwaſion.</hi> Many, or moſt of you are not ignorant of the bitter Words and Deportment that have dropt from the Tongues and Pens of many againſt their Brethren, becauſe of their differing Apprehenſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the moſt High God: and now thus far are we come, ſcanning the difference, and it remains in this narrow Corner; for all are agreed that that Glorious Eternal Being, whoſe Throne is in the Heavens, or the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens is his Throne, whom the Heaven and Heaven of Heavens cannot contain, whoſe Preſence fills Heaven and Earth, even that this Glorious Being or Eſſence, and he <hi>only,</hi> from everlaſting to everlaſting is the one and <hi>only</hi> moſt High God, the Original of all Power, Authority, Wiſdom, Life, Light, Knowledg, Nature, Perfection, Goodneſs, Bounty, Mercy, Juſtice, Love, Action, and Being. And further, you are all agreed that this very Eſſence is an impartible, <hi>uncompound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> Eſſence: So that our differing Brethren own the ſame moſt High, the <hi>ſame</hi> Eſſence for <hi>Number, Nature, and Kind,</hi> owning <hi>all</hi> and <hi>whole</hi> of the Divine <hi>Eſſence</hi> and eſſential <hi>Properties,</hi> as full in <hi>all</hi> reſpects as we our ſelves, not abating one of them, no nor any <hi>part</hi> of one of them, worſhipping it with the <hi>ſame,</hi> and as much Adoration and Reſpect as we our <hi>ſelves,</hi> owning the very <hi>ſame</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and <hi>no</hi> other: So that the difference is not about <hi>Subſtance,</hi> Matter, or Properties; but only about a certain <hi>Manner</hi> or <hi>Mode</hi> of ſubſiſting: yea yet further, both agreeing that whatever is God moſt High, whether Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence or Property, tho improper to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh it, is <hi>all</hi> and <hi>whole</hi> in the <hi>Perſon</hi> of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:96824:9"/> 
                     <hi>Father.</hi> This none of us all <hi>dare</hi> deny: for then we ſhall throw down our own Opinion, Root and Branch. Nay further, it is joint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agreed b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> that whatſoever is God moſt High, whether Eſſence, Attribute, or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, it is <hi>all</hi> in <hi>every one,</hi> and conſequently in the <hi>Father:</hi> See Mr. <hi>Monk</hi> pag. 38. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a Perſon ſignifies both the Eſſence and its Relative Property, all the Perſons having one and the ſame Eſſence, it followeth that in reſpect of the Eſſence one perſon <hi>is in another.</hi> Thus all amounts to thus much: You ſay that Eſſence, and all that we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly call God, and worſhip, is in the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Father, and ſo ſay they: only you require them to confeſs that the Eſſence ſubſiſteth not <hi>only</hi> thus, but <hi>alſo</hi> in <hi>two</hi> other diſtinct <hi>Manners</hi> or <hi>Modes:</hi> This is all. And truly methinks it looks like a very hard caſe, that our Brethren ſhould own the whole Eſſence with all its Royal and Eſſential Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and likewiſe own all his mighty Works of old, and now, whereby he hath made himſelf known, and likewiſe reverence and honour it as highly as our ſelves; and yet we muſt exclude them Communion at the Table of the Lord, <hi>only</hi> and meerly for a <hi>Circumſtance,</hi> that is, a differing <hi>Manner</hi> or Mode of ſubſiſting; which yet alſo is ſo <hi>dark</hi> and dubious, that not one of us durſt once <hi>touch</hi> it with our Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> to explain it. Shall we then be ſo poſitive, ſo highly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited of our own Judgments in ſo <hi>intricate,</hi> ſo myſterious a Matter, which yet at moſt is but a <hi>Circumſtance, (viz.</hi> a Mode or Manner of ſubſiſting) not <hi>any</hi> part of the thing it ſelf, the Eſſence it ſelf? Shall we cenſure, condemn, and ſtigmatize our good Brethren, every way elſe as able for Parts, Knowledg, Purity of Manners, and zealous for God and his Ways as our ſelves? Shall we repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them Denyers of the true God, Broach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Hereſies, nay damnable Hereſies? Surely no: Be it far from us; leſt it be thought that an evil Mind hath had dominion over us: more eſpecially, ſince admitting their Sentiments to be in this caſe circumſtantially erroneous (for a <hi>Hereſy</hi> I will not allow it) yet it hinders not at all, or is no Impediment to our paying Adoration or Worſhip to the moſt High, as I ſhall come to ſhew in the next Section. But firſt let me obſerve unto you that all thoſe things reſpecting the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and eſſential Properties wherein we and all our Brethren are agreed, both Scripture and Reaſon in all plainneſs teaches: But this controverſal part concerning the treble Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner or Mode of the ſubſiſting of the Divine Eſſence, is neither taught by <hi>Reaſon,</hi> nor found in, or is Scripture-Language; I ſay, it is not <hi>Scripture</hi>-Language, but only drawn from ſome Inferences and Conſequences of and from the holy Scripture. I ſay, when we have only Conſequences to foot upon in a caſe of this nature and difficulty, ſtill it calls for the more <hi>Moderation</hi> and Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs towards perſons of differing Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in ſuch a <hi>tender</hi> point, who withal are as orthodox in the <hi>main</hi> every way as our ſelves. But now I come to the next point.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. III.</hi> Concerning the manner how we ought to pay our Worſhip and Adoration to this one moſt High God.</head>
                  <p>IN the creating of this I ſhall include and reſolve this following Queſtion: Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be the <hi>declared</hi> Pleaſure of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hty that his Subjects ſhould pay their Ado<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ation to the <hi>Matter</hi> ſubſiſting, or the <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>r</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſiſting?</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ully thus: Whether it be the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>ſure of the Almighty that his Subiects ſhould pay their Adoration unto him with and under the Conception and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation of <hi>One</hi> Supream Soveraign ſingle Subſtance, unſeparable in Eſſence and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Properties, ſubſiſting in <hi>one</hi> Perſon? Or, whether it be his pleaſure it ſhould be paid unto him under the notion and appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of a <hi>ſingle</hi> Eſſence ſubſiſting in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:96824:9"/> 
                     <hi>three</hi> diſtinct <hi>Manners, Modes, or Perſons?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the reſolving of this Queſtion I ſhall premiſe this by the way: That the Order, Manner, or Mode of paying our Ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ration, and our Conceptions of the Object of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in the Act of Worſhip ought not to be regulated by our Conceptions, but to be decided merely by the <hi>Directi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n</hi> and Rule God is pleaſed to give us about it in his Word. For it is not what we think fit, but what he ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is moſt proper, and our Duty: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re I take this f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r granted, that the H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly Scr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ptures are our only whole ſufficient Rule to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uide us in all points of Faith and go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d Manners reſpecting Salvation, to guide us in the underſtanding of the Object and Act of Worſhip, and in our conception of the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject in the Act thereof.</p>
                  <p>And for want of keeping cloſe to this Rule, ſo many Innovations and Inſtit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> have been introduced; people thinking ſtill to mend things by bringing it nearer to their own Conceptions, have often made it worſe in not heeding the Standard.</p>
                  <p>Theſe things p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>emiſed, I ſhall give my Anſwer to the Queſtion, and do ſay, that to me it doth not a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pear that it is the pleaſure of God that Worſhip ſhould be paid unto him under the <hi>appellati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n,</hi> and with the <hi>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception</hi> of a ſingle Eſſence ſubſiſting b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th in <hi>one and three</hi> diſtinct Manners, Modes, or Perſons.</p>
                  <p>But <hi>rather</hi> that it is his declared Will that his Subjects ſhould pay their Adoration to him under, and with the conception and appellation of <hi>one</hi> ſupream Soveraign and ſingular Subſtance, inſepar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ble in Eſſence and Divine Properties, ſubſiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng in <hi>one Divine Perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n</hi> and Spirit. And for this I will give my Reaſons.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, as hath been hinted, I take it for granted that let the Doctrine of three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in one Eſſence be as clear as the Sun, yet with wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> conceptions we muſt worſhip muſt be <hi>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ble</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> God's Word: B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t now to the Reaſons. My firſt Reaſon i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, notwithſtanding the various Appellatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> which God choſe in f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rmer Diſpenſations to make himſelf kno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n to his S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bjects by as the Object of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rſhip, tho they did plainly diſcover the Unity of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nce, and alſo his eſſential Properties, yet I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member not <hi>one</hi> Diſcovery of him as a ſingle Eſſence in a <hi>threefold</hi> ſubſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, or one Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and three P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. And there ſeems no ſuch diſcovery under the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Diſpenſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Which will app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>r, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>irſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> take notice how he diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>over<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> himſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> in gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ral, both at firſt to <hi>Adam;</hi> ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ndly to <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and alſo after the F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ood, and hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> forth the Law to the Generations <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Flood; alſo to <hi>Abraham, I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>, Jac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>, M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> and to <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rael</hi> in general; and in partic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lar in giving ſorth his Law. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>ral to all ſuch as he make<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> diſcovery of himſelf as the Object of their Worſhip, he ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s uſe of ſuch Denominations <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ngu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar number, as <hi>I, M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>;</hi> and not <hi>we,</hi> or <hi>ours.</hi> Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ewiſe w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> did mention this ſacred <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> in p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>, their Worſhip, they made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſuch E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, as ſhewed it was th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ir S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt that they conceived of him as <hi>one</hi> intire O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and not <hi>one</hi> and <hi>three;</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Thee, Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Thou, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r Thine; not Ye, You, Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>r, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Yours: which ſhews that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hateve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved</hi> of different Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns in that one ſin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Eſſence, or an <hi>one</hi> intire Subſtance in a <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold</hi> Manner or Mode of ſubſiſting (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> yet no where <hi>appears</hi> that they, or any o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> before-named did) but if ſo, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> reſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, yet it appears they <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ught</hi> it th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ir Duty t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> give Appellations to denominate, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently to conceive of the Obiect o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ir Worſhip as a ſingle one in one Perſon, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent Being, without thinking it ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial to take notice of Name, of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of a threefold manner of ſubſiſtin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le Eſſence both in one and three, in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t of Worſhip; which yet ſure, were th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial</hi> and eſſential a part of right <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rſhi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, (as now ſuppoſed) methin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> have appeared, if not in <hi>all,</hi> yet a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſt in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of the many Inſtanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s we have in Scri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ture, of Perſons expre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mſelves in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of Worſhip and Adoration.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>w to return <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>irſt, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t, Gods diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ring hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> to man: In th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> firſt place to avoid an Obj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, I am not ſpea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing of what i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96824:10"/> ſpeaks concerning making Man, or going down to ſee the Builders of <hi>Babel;</hi> for this is fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign to my preſent buſineſs (which is not now to diſpute <hi>pro</hi> or <hi>con,</hi> either to <hi>prove</hi> or <hi>deny</hi> the Doctrine of three Perſons in one Eſſence) but my particular Buſineſs is to ſhew how God hath <hi>diſcovered</hi> himſelf to Man. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let none cry out and ſay, you have forgot the word <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> in the forenamed places: For, firſt, whether it be there pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ciſely demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated three undivided Perſons in one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent Being, the Diſſenters from <hi>Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi>'s Creed will not be wanting to bring Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to the contrary, which (as aforeſaid) is not now my <hi>buſineſs</hi> to take notice of. But, ſecondly, obſerve if they do, yet theſe are Words ſpoken in Heaven, which no mortal Man did ever h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ar, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re they directed to man, but ſpoken in the Heav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nly Manſions by him who perfectly knows and underſtands himſelf. But that which I inſiſt upon is, that always when God directs his Speech to Man, or Men, <hi>diſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>vering</hi> himſelf to them as the Object of their Worſhip, he the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſpeaks in the <hi>ſingular</hi> number. Now this I take for granted, becauſe I think it will not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e denied that the Manner or Mode of God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> deſcribing of himſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Man, as the Object of their Worſhip, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ght to be the Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our Conceptions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f him in the Act of Worſhip: And that this is not plural, but ſingular, will appear in the particular Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the above-hinted Inſtances.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. To begin with <hi>Adam,</hi> Gen. 3.11. <hi>Haſt thou eaten of the T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ee, where<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f</hi> I <hi>command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d that thou ſhouldſt not eat?</hi> and ver. 15. I <hi>will put enmity,</hi> &amp;c. Then to <hi>Noah,</hi> Gen. 6.13. <hi>And God ſaid unt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Noah, <hi>The end of all Fleſh is come before</hi> M E, <hi>and behold</hi> I <hi>will deſtroy them:</hi> ver. 17. <hi>Behold</hi> I, <hi>even</hi> I <hi>do bring a Flood of Waters.</hi> Ver. 18. <hi>But with thee will</hi> I <hi>eſtabliſh my Covenant.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. The like, or the ſame Expreſſions you have, <hi>Chap.</hi> 7. at ver. 1, 4. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 9. In the Deed, Contract, or Covenant, whereby God makes himſelf <hi>kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>wn</hi> to, and with the new World after the Deluge, we find him thus expreſſing himſelf, ver. 3. <hi>The green Herb have</hi> I <hi>given you.</hi> Ver. 5. <hi>Your Blood of your lives will</hi> I <hi>require, at the hand of every Beaſt will</hi> I <hi>require it; and at the hand of every Man's Brother will</hi> I <hi>require it.</hi> Ver. 9. <hi>And</hi> I, <hi>even</hi> I <hi>eſtabliſh</hi> my <hi>Covenant with you.</hi> Ver. 11. <hi>And I will eſtabliſh</hi> my <hi>Covenant with you.</hi> Ver. 13. I <hi>do ſet</hi> my <hi>Bow in the Cloud.</hi> Ver. 15. <hi>And</hi> I <hi>will remember my Covenant which is between</hi> Me <hi>and you, and every living Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of all Fleſh; and the Waters ſhall no more become a Flood to deſtroy all Fleſh.</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, the Covenant made with all Fleſh, was under the notion of a <hi>ſingle</hi> Being, and not a <hi>threefold</hi> ſubſiſting.</p>
                  <p>Now touching God's diſcovering and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing himſelf to <hi>Abraham</hi> the firſt time, <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.1, 2, 3. <hi>Get thee into a Land that</hi> I <hi>ſhall ſhew thee; and</hi> I <hi>will make of thee a great Nation: And I will bleſs thee, and</hi> I <hi>will bleſs them that bleſs thee.</hi> The ſecond time of appearance, <hi>ver.</hi> 7. <hi>And the Lord appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto</hi> Abram, <hi>and ſaid, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto thy Seed will</hi> I <hi>give this Land.</hi> The third time of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.15, 16. Fourth time of appearance, <hi>Chap.</hi> 15.1. <hi>The word of the Lord came unto</hi> Abraham <hi>in a Viſion ſaying, Fear not,</hi> I <hi>am thy Shield.</hi> Likewiſe <hi>ver.</hi> 7, 14, 18. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 17.1, 2. at the making the Covenant the Lord appeared unto <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>id, I <hi>am the Almighty God, walk b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>fore</hi> Me, <hi>and be thou perfect; and</hi> I <hi>will make</hi> My <hi>Covenant between</hi> Me <hi>and thee.</hi> But not to mention any more of <hi>Abraham,</hi> which we might, let it ſuffice that at every appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance recorded it was never with a <hi>plural</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination.</p>
                  <p>Next, for <hi>Iſaac,</hi> Chap. 26.2, 3, 4, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>And the Lord appeared unto him, and ſaid, Go not down into</hi> Egypt; <hi>dwell in the Land which I ſhall tell thee of, ſojourn in this Land, and</hi> I <hi>will be with thee, and will bleſs thee, and unto thy Seed</hi> I <hi>will give all theſe Countries; and</hi> I <hi>will pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>form the Oath which</hi> I <hi>ſware unto</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham <hi>thy Father; and</hi> I <hi>will make thy Seed to multiply. Becauſe that</hi> Abraham <hi>obeyed</hi> my <hi>Voic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, and kept</hi> my <hi>Charge,</hi> my <hi>Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> my <hi>Statutes, and my Laws.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Next, for <hi>Jacob,</hi> Chap. 28. verſ. 13, 15. <hi>And behold, the Lord ſtood above it, and ſaid, I am the Lord God of</hi> Abraham <hi>thy Father, and the God of</hi> Iſaac; <hi>the Land whereon thou lyeſt, to thee will</hi> I <hi>give it. And behold,</hi> I <hi>am
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:96824:10"/> with thee, and will keep thee in all places whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou goeſt, and will bring thee again into this Land: for</hi> I <hi>will not leave thee until</hi> I <hi>have done that which I have ſpoken.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Next we come to <hi>Moſes,</hi> Exodus 3. ver. 6. <hi>Moreover he ſaid,</hi> I <hi>am the God of thy Father, the God of</hi> Abraham, <hi>the God of</hi> Iſaac, <hi>and the God of</hi> Jacob. And in ver. 13, 14, 15. the moſt High is particularly deſired by <hi>Moſes</hi> upon an emergent occaſion to diſcover himſelf, that he and <hi>Iſrael</hi> might know how to conceive of him aright. And God gives him particular di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection what to ſay: <hi>And</hi> Moſes <hi>ſaid unto God, Behold, when I come unto the Children of</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, <hi>and ſhall ſay unto them, The God of your Fathers hath ſent me unto you; and they ſhall ſay to me, What is his name? what ſhall I ſay unto them? And God ſaid unto</hi> Moſes, I AM <hi>that</hi> I AM; <hi>and he ſaid, Thus ſhalt thou ſay unto the Children of</hi> Iſrael, I AM <hi>hath ſent me unto you.</hi> And God ſaid moreover unto <hi>Moſes, Thus ſhalt thou ſay unto the Children of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>The Lord God of your Fathers, the God of</hi> Abraham, <hi>the God of</hi> Iſaac, <hi>and the God of</hi> Jacob <hi>hath ſent me unto you: this is my name for ever, and this is my memorial unto all Generations.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now ſurely if the conception of a Trinity of Perſons in God were ſo abſolutely neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary in the Act of Worſhip as is now taught, who can but ſuppoſe that the Almighty, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially being ſo <hi>particularly</hi> deſired to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare himſelf, and that alſo in order, and to the end that <hi>Iſrael</hi> might put their truſt, and act faith in him aright; who can think, I ſay, but that the Almighty would have m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de a <hi>plain</hi> diſcovery thereof in this place? On the other ſide; tho God do here make himſelf known by ſuch Names or Memorials as ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently diſcover the Oneneſs of his Being, and alſo his eſſential Properties, both Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, Goodneſs, Wiſdom, Truth, Love, Bounty, Juſtice, and the reſt, which were all diſcovered to <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> whoſe God he here declares himſelf to be; yet what Man not prepoſſeſſed can ever ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that God intended, or <hi>Iſrael</hi> could by this Deſcription of God, conceive of him as a <hi>threef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ld</hi> ſubſiſtence?</p>
                  <p>And to the end that you may ſee the ſcope of this Deſcription in others Opinions as well as my own, I will quote two Authors: firſt, Mr. <hi>Monk</hi> in the Book forecited, <hi>page</hi> 25. <q rend="margSglQuotes">
                        <hi>I AM,</hi> that is (ſaith he) I am the only true God, truly ſubſiſting, and not only through the opinion of Men as Id<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ls are: I am he that hath an everlaſting Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, unchangeably ſubſiſting of it ſelf, not depending upon others, infinite, <hi>moſt ſimple,</hi> the Author and Cauſe of the being of all things: not a borrowed, changeable, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, dependent, and <hi>compound</hi> Being, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as all the Creatures have: Of this mine Eſſence will I give thee the higheſt, moſt expreſs and general name of all, <hi>[He that is.]</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, I ſhall quote Mr. <hi>Preſton</hi> in his forecited Book, <hi>page</hi> 96. <q rend="margSglQuotes">As if he ſhould ſay, if yet they cannot underſtand what this name is, it is the ſame that I was known by to <hi>Abraham,</hi> to <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and to <hi>Jacob:</hi> what I was to them, the ſame will I be to you. I was known to them by my Word, and by my Works, and by my Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles; and the ſame ſhall you find me: it is that God which hath ſent me unto you [this is my name.] Which Words are to be referred not only to the latter Words, but to the former, <hi>I AM THAT I AM.</hi>
                     </q> Thus far Mr. <hi>Preſton.</hi> And thus you ſee here is nothing perceived in this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of a <hi>Trinity</hi> of Perſons in others Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, or our own Reaſon.</p>
                  <p>The next diſcovery of himſelf we find in <hi>Exod.</hi> 6.23. <hi>And God ſpake unto</hi> Moſes, <hi>and ſaid,</hi> I <hi>am the Lord: And</hi> I <hi>appeared unto</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, <hi>and unto</hi> Iſaac, <hi>and unto</hi> Jacob, <hi>by the name of God Almighty, but by my Name</hi> JEHOVAH <hi>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s I n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t known t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> them.</hi> Here I note two things: firſt, that God doth plainly here declare how he taught and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected <hi>Abraham, Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> to act Faith in, and <hi>conceive</hi> of him, <hi>viz.</hi> as a God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, All-powerful, All-ſufficient, All-wiſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But he mentions not in the leaſt his ſubſiſting in a <hi>Trinity.</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>condly, I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that God doth here m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll, copious, profound and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le <hi>Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>very</hi> of himſelf to his Subjects than at any time heretofore, by giving them his Name <hi>JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HOVAH,</hi> being the cleareſt and moſt proper name of his Being and undivided eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:96824:11"/> inſeparable Properties: which ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Name the Jews deſervedly and greatly rever<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nce; inſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>much that the Author of the Book, intituled, <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Father's Spectacles to behold his Child,</hi> ſaith in his 110. page, the Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s hold it n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> to uſe the name <hi>JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HOVAH</hi> at all, but by the Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>y only, and that but once a year. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>r, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>JEHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VAH</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> nev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r prono<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> on pain of Dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, only by the Prieſt in the <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>torum,</hi> and that on the day of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n, be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> once a year. And yet notwithſtanding thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> further Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>covery, and their great Reverence to the Name, I do not underſtand that <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ael</hi> did thereby c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ncei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> a diſtinction of <hi>Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ns</hi> in that <hi>one</hi> Eſſence h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ld forth thereby. And I perce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve the Author (my Reſpected F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iend) laſt cited in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> and 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>page,</hi> when he paraphraſes on the word (tho he be a Diſciple of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ene Creed) yet notes not a diſtinction of <hi>Per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ns</hi> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rectly and properly flowing, as the genuine ſenſe of this Word: But that properly and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly it imports and expreſſes the Divine Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with all the eſſential Properties. And the moſt that I can remember I ever read in any Author treating of this Word, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted to no more but this, <hi>viz.</hi> That this ſacred Name of the moſt High, was the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and proper Name of the Divine <hi>Eſſence,</hi> and all its inſeparable Properties, tho not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding, yet not declaring, diſcovering or revealing it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r a <hi>threefold perſonal</hi> ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſiſting.</p>
                  <p>But further; when God <hi>diſcovers</hi> himſelf as the only Object of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r Worſhip, prefixed in the fore fr nt of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Holy Law, <hi>Exodus</hi> 2.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Firſt, he declares him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> name; <hi>I am the Lord thy God:</hi> Secondly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> his Works; <hi>Which hath br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ught thee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ut <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>nd of</hi> Egy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. In the firſt Verſe is the Attr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>te <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>nſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: <hi>I the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> jeal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ting the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ty,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c. The <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th</hi> Verſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>tai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Att<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>te of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Love: <hi>She<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ng M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t love m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> The Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties were man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d in the W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rſt mentioned, viz. <hi>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> them</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> where his Patience, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Pity, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Wiſdo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, his Power were eminently ſhewn.</p>
                  <p>Methinks, as aforeſaid, if it had been the will of God that <hi>Iſrael</hi> his peculiar Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould have worſhipped him with the <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nception</hi> of a <hi>Trinity</hi> in the <hi>Act</hi> of Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on, that then he would, in this place <hi>eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> have diſcovered ſomething thereof, ſince he is here more amply diſcovering his <hi>Will</hi> and their <hi>Duty</hi> than at any time heretofore. And yet here appears no ſuch thing; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtill the Object of Worſhip is diſcovered under the notion of a <hi>ſingle Being,</hi> I <hi>am the Lord.</hi> And this with his Works and At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes, appears to be all the Deſcription of him.</p>
                  <p>Then again, at <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſes</hi> his repeating that which our Saviour calls the firſt and great Commandment, containing the principal part of Duty and Worſhip to this ſacred <hi>Object,</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>face runs thus, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.4. <hi>He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> O</hi> Iſr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>el, <hi>the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rd our God is One Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>deed it is reaſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>able to conclude that God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tended his Subjects ſhould wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him under the notion, appellation, and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tion of <hi>One.</hi> But who can think that by this he intended to teach them to do it under the notion and appellation of <hi>three?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly, as touching God's diſcovering of himſelf under the ſomer Diſpenſation: Tho I confeſs when the words Holy <hi>One</hi> are uſed, they do not always particularly reſpect the moſt High, yet whenever they are uſed in holy Writ, as moſt proper, ſo they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways uſed to ſignify a <hi>ſingle</hi> Perſon. Now tho I ſhall not cite the particulars being too large, yet I promiſe to any that ſhall ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly deſire it, <hi>thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ty</hi> ſeveral places in the Old Teſtament, where he is denominated the <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ly One;</hi> and I can be better than my word. And on the other ſide, I challenge any body to ſhew me one place where he calls himſelf, or is called the <hi>Holy Three:</hi> and if ſo, it is a ſtrong preſumption at leaſt, that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>uld be worſhipped under the notion of a h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly <hi>One,</hi> or <hi>ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d thus having <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> over ſome of the moſt prin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> places wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e God hath diſcovered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to his Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s, and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llected them t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>r, I conceive any indiff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ent Perſon, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ſt ſeriouſly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:96824:11"/> that any perſon having no other grounds to conceive a <hi>Trinity</hi> of perſons in this <hi>one Eſſence</hi> than what ariſes from thoſe Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; it is not likely he ſhould be induced by thoſe Paſſages to conceive a <hi>Trinity</hi> of Perſons in this <hi>one Eſſence</hi> and Object.</p>
                  <p>Not th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t I hereby (as aforeſaid) <hi>deny</hi> the thing it ſelf, <hi>viz.</hi> the Doctrine of three Perſons; but ſhew that it is not likely that the Almighty doth <hi>require</hi> a particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of <hi>three</hi> Perſons in the act of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, but only <hi>one;</hi> ſince he hath left the notion of <hi>three</hi> ſo very dark, as indeed not diſcernable, in thoſe <hi>very</hi> places where he diſcovers himſelf as the <hi>Object</hi> of Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: And hath choſen ſuch Epithets to declare himſelf generally and univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally, as properly do infer a <hi>ſingle</hi> Eſſence not revealed, as ſubſiſting in <hi>three</hi> Somewhats, Manners, Modes, or Perſons.</p>
                  <p>And further, it is obſervable that the holy Scriptures ſpeaking of, and holding forth the <hi>One</hi> moſt High, do often repeat the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his <hi>ſingle</hi> undivided Eſſence, as alſo the Greatneſs of his Power, his Wiſdom, and the Reſidue of his <hi>Eſſential Properties:</hi> they are ſound in multitudes of places in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as if Perſons could never enough be told, and made ſenſible of thoſe things, wherein all Parties are <hi>agreed;</hi> and as if they could never have too powerful conceptions of it in the Act of Worſhip. Methinks therefore it is ſtrange, that ſo eſpecial a point, as this is thought to be, ſhould be left ſo dark and obſcure, even to that degree that a man without any other help than thoſe Scriptures of the Old Teſtament <hi>(of which now I ſpeak)</hi> which ſpeak directly of the moſt High as the Object to be worſhipped; I ſay, may almoſt (if not altogether) as ſoon conceive in his mind <hi>three hundred diſtinct Perſons</hi> in this <hi>Eſſence</hi> as conceive <hi>three.</hi> What f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llows hence then but that that Perſon w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ich ſincerely worſhips the moſt High, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> of him as ſubſiſting in <hi>one</hi> undi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſence, in <hi>one</hi> Perſon, as we on all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e him to do, and worſhips him with ſuch Sentiments as he in conſcience thinks th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe plain Paſſages before recited do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>turally hold f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rth; what hinders, I ſay, but that we may think that he worſhips the moſt High aright, and according to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, altho he <hi>diſtinguiſhes</hi> not the Manners or Modes of his ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſting? which indeed in it ſelf is ſomething hard to the unle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rned at leaſt, to diſtinguiſh in their thou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hts <hi>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> diſtinct perſons, and not alſo at the ſame time to conceive <hi>three real ſubſtantial</hi> diſtinct Beings or Subſtances.</p>
                  <p>I therefore humbly, conceive that thoſe that think they ought, and find they can in the act of Worſhip diſtinguiſh the Perſons, and not at the ſame time divide in their thoughts the Subſtance, I ſay let them <hi>do ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>:</hi> and they that think themſelves not obliged, and think they cannot well make this diſtinction in their thoughts, my opinion is, let them alone to ſerve God after the <hi>old faſhion</hi> that <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> ſerved God in: And not for ſo ſmall a matter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ſtigmatized as A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts, Denyers of the true God, Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ticks, and ſuch other infamous Characters, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting good Manners.</p>
                  <p>But in the next place: having ſhewn in the foregoing Diſcourſe how God hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted himſelf, I now in the ſecond place come to ſhew how, or in what manner the aforeſaid <hi>Adam, Abraham, Ja<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> b, Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> did conceive of the moſt H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>h when they addreſſed themſelves unto him: which appears not to reſpect his ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſting, but his <hi>Eſſence</hi> and eſſential Properties, which yet further con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>irms it, that either they were ignorant of a <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hreefold</hi> ſubſiſting, or elſe did not think it expedient or neceſſary to contain it in their c nceptions as a neceſſary part of, and in Divine Worſhip: This in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral will appear, in that they always uſed ſuch Exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns as belong to the <hi>ſingular</hi> number, as <hi>thee, thy, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n,</hi> or <hi>thine;</hi> which ſhew that they did not directly pay their reſpects to <hi>diſtinct</hi> Perſon, but t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>nc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> without <hi>diſtinction;</hi> ſince <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>r read that they made uſe of <hi>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>, y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> or <hi>yours.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But to make it more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lain, we will exa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mine the particular Inſtances. Firſt, <hi>Adam,</hi> Gen. 3.10, 11. he ſaid, <hi>I heard</hi> thy <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ice, and the W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>man whom</hi> thou <hi>gaveſt me,</hi> &amp;c. Next <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 15.2. <hi>And</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>raham
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:96824:12"/> 
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>d, Lord God, what wilt</hi> thou <hi>give me?</hi> Chap. 17.18. <hi>O that</hi> Iſmael <hi>might live before</hi> Thee! And when he would make his Servant ſwear by the <hi>True</hi> God, <hi>Chap.</hi> 24.3. he did <hi>not</hi> diſtinguiſh him as <hi>one in three,</hi> but ſays he, <hi>I will make thee ſwear by the Lord, the God of Heaven, and the God of the Earth!</hi> Alſo when the Servant ſeveral times in this Chapter di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects his Prayer to this God, he doth not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh him perſonally in <hi>three;</hi> but ſays, <hi>O Lord God of my Maſter</hi> Abraham, <hi>I pray</hi> thee <hi>ſend me good ſpeed.</hi> Then for <hi>Jacob,</hi> when he tells his Father <hi>Laban</hi> how his Subſtance came to be increaſed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.42. he doth not ſay the God ſubſiſting in <hi>three</hi> Perſons, but ſays he, <hi>the God of my Father, the God of</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and Chap. 32.10. <hi>I am not worthy of the Mercies, and all the Truth which</hi> Thou <hi>haſt ſhewed me.</hi> Ver. 11. <hi>Deliver me I pray thee. And thou ſaidſt, I will ſurely do thee good.</hi> In ſhort, in ſeveral places he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhes him <hi>verbatim</hi> as God diſcovered himſelf to <hi>Abraham, viz.</hi> God Almighty, but not one word of God in <hi>three</hi> Perſons. Next <hi>Moſes,</hi> Exodus 5.23. <hi>For ſince I came to</hi> Pharaoh <hi>to ſpeak in</hi> Thy <hi>Name, he hath done evil to this People. Neither haſt</hi> Thou <hi>delivered</hi> thy <hi>People at all.</hi> Chap. 15.1. <hi>Then ſang</hi> Moſes <hi>and the Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>this Song unto the Lord: He hath triumphed gloriouſly, the Horſe and his Rider hath</hi> He <hi>thrown into the Sea.</hi> And in this Song you have the Terms, <hi>he, thee, thy, thou, thine, him,</hi> repeated no leſs than 35 <hi>times,</hi> and yet neither <hi>you, yours, they</hi> or <hi>them</hi> once mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, reſpecting the moſt High. Thus have I briefly run over the ſum of the moſt remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Inſtances of perſons paying their Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to the moſt High in the Old Teſtament; and I might have inſtanced <hi>David, Solomon, Daniel,</hi> and many others, yea down to <hi>Zecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riah</hi>'s days: and it appears as if they were all agreed to conceive of, and acknowledg an <hi>undivided, ſingle Eſſence,</hi> and its Properties. But no Footſteps do appear of their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing the Eſſence in <hi>three</hi> perſons in their Conceptions. And if the Iſraelites ever had any ſuch conception of God, methinks it ſhould not be loſt; and if not loſt, it is ſtrange <hi>Joſephus</hi> ſhould not mention it, ſince he gives an account of things as far back as <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> even from the beginning; and often ſpeaks of God and his eſſential Properties, deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing the true Object of the Jews Worſhip, and yet always ſpeaks of him as <hi>one</hi> in <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of <hi>Eſſence,</hi> but hints not a word of <hi>divers</hi> Perſons. And as <hi>Joſephus</hi> then, ſo the <hi>Jews</hi> now acknowledg no ſuch thing, as Mr. <hi>Monk</hi> ſays page 70. he ſays the Doctrine of the Trinity is contrary to the Blindneſs of the Jews, who do affirm an Eſſence altogether without <hi>diſtinction.</hi> Now, I ſay, 'tis ſtrange if this were underſtood amongſt them (eſpecially as ſo <hi>material</hi> a thing as is now ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed) that then both the Jews now (who yet profeſs the true God, and are zealous of the Moſaical Law) and <hi>Joſephus</hi> ſo long ago, ſhould yet be ignorant of ſo remarkable a matter.</p>
                  <p>In the next place, I come to the <hi>New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament,</hi> to ſee whether we may judg it the Will of God that we ſhould worſhip and adore his Eſſence, as ſubſiſting in <hi>one</hi> Perſon, or in <hi>three:</hi> And firſt I will conſider the Apoſtle <hi>Stephen,</hi> what he ſays of the moſt High, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.2. he calls him, <hi>the God of Glory;</hi> and ver. 32. he cites and deſcribes the antient Deſcription without enlarging, viz. <hi>I am the God of</hi> Abraham, and the God of <hi>Iſaac, and</hi> the God of <hi>Jacob.</hi> And ver. 48. <hi>The moſt High dwells not in Temples made with Hands.</hi> Herein is a diſcovery of God's Greatneſs, but no <hi>diſtinguiſhing</hi> his Perſons. And remarkable it is that <hi>Paul</hi> about to inſtruct the ignorant <hi>Athenians</hi> in the knowledg of the true God, as the Object of their Worſhip, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.23, 24, 25. firſt lets them know that they ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly worſhipped the unknown God, and that <hi>him</hi> he would declare unto them: And accordingly ſays, <hi>God that made the World, and all things therein, ſeeing that he is Lord of Heaven and Earth, dwells not in Temples made with mens hands, as though he needed any thing, ſeeing he giveth to all Life, and Breath, and all things.</hi> Herein the Apoſtle very notably ſets forth his moſt glorious Attributes, and inviſible Being, by his creating and preſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all things: But ſays not one word of the <hi>diſtinction</hi> of Perſons. Now if t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Knowledg of this were ſo neceſſary to be
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:96824:12"/> known in order to Salvation as is imagined; <hi>Paul</hi> had no leſs need to inſtruct theſe ignorant <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> therein, as much as in the Knowledg of the <hi>Eſſential</hi> Properties and Power. Next we will conſider <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.6. <hi>There is</hi> One <hi>God and Father of all, who is above all.</hi> Here you ſee a plain diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of the Godhead, and his Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, but the <hi>Deſcription</hi> of Perſons is ſtill want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. To this I will add 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.6. <hi>But to us there is but</hi> One God, <hi>the Father of all things.</hi> Here again the Object of Worſhip is deſcribed as the firſt Cauſe and Foundation of all things <hi>(of whom are all things.)</hi> 2. The Inſeparableneſs and <hi>Oneneſs</hi> of his Being is aſſerted (but <hi>One</hi> God.) 3. He is ſo far from directing us to fix our Conceptions on him, as diſtinguiſhed into <hi>three</hi> Perſons, that he ſolely centers him in <hi>One,</hi> even as ſubſiſting in the <hi>Father.</hi> Now what rational Man can conclude from hence, but that we are to conceive of the Object of Worſhip as intirely ſubſiſting in, and to be called by the Appellation of the <hi>Father,</hi> and ſo to be worſhipped? That is, in plainneſs, that we are to conceive that all that we believe to be God moſt High, whether Eſſence, Attributes, or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whatever we may think of its various ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in our <hi>ſelves,</hi> yet it is to be adored and diſtinguiſhed by the Perſon of the <hi>Father;</hi> where we all ſay that 'tis <hi>all and whole.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But further, I ſhall add the Authority of him who cannot err. John 4.22, 23, 24. <hi>Ye worſhip ye know not what: We know what we worſhip; for Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is of the</hi> Jews.—<hi>But the hour cometh, and now is, when the true Worſhippers ſhall worſhip the</hi> Father <hi>in Spirit and in Truth: for the Father ſeeketh ſuch to worſhip</hi> him. <hi>God is a Spirit, and they that worſhip Him, muſt worſhip Him in Spirit and in Truth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From this pertinent place I note as follows; Firſt, That it contains a Diſcourſe of our Saviour <hi>directly</hi> concerning Worſhip: 1. Blaming and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing the ignorant <hi>falſe</hi> Worſhippers; <hi>Ye,</hi> the <hi>Samaritans, worſhip ye know not what.</hi> 2. Deſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the true Worſhippers: 1. By the manner how, <hi>in Spirit and in Truth.</hi> 2. The Matter or Object what; and that deſcribed two ways: 1ſt. His <hi>Eſſence,</hi> a Spirit: 2dly. The <hi>Perſon</hi> who, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Father; the true Worſhippers ſhall worſhip the Father.</hi> Further, from this Text I obſerve; 1. They can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be true Worſhippers that worſhip they know not what. 2. They that worſhip the Father as the proper Object of Divine Worſhip, are not ſuch as worſhip they know not what, but ſuch as know what they worſhip. 3. They that worſhip the Father, conceiving of him, as containing the glorious inſeparable Eſſence or Spirit, being wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy above all things to be worſhipped; theſe I ſay are not the falſe, but the <hi>true</hi> Worſhippers of God; and provided they perform their Worſhip ſpiritually, ſhall be accepted by him, becauſe he ſeeks ſuch to worſhip him. 4. That it is the Will of God, and Direction of Chriſt, that of all the Perſons believed to be in the Deity, God the <hi>Father</hi> is to be conceived as the moſt proper <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> for us to direct our higheſt Adoration to. 5. That he that conceives that the Godhead, and all its eſſential Properties, ſubſiſt in the Father as the proper Object of Divine Worſhip, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives not amiſs; becauſe, according to Chriſt's Rule, he is a <hi>true</hi> Worſhipper. 6. That we may lawfully have Communion with any ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, if that be all their fault, becauſe they are true Worſhippers, and with better we cannot well join. 7. I obſerve that when Chriſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes the Object of our Worſhip, he is ſo far from diſtinguiſhing or teaching us to diſtinguiſh the Perſons in that Object, that he contains all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the denomination of <hi>one only</hi> Perſon, even the <hi>Father.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Next I ſhall cite the Inſtruction of our Lord, expreſly injoining us to <hi>pay</hi> Adoration to God the <hi>Father,</hi> and acknowledg all to be his. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.9. <hi>After this manner therefore pray ye: Our Father who art in Heaven, hallowed be</hi> thy <hi>Name;</hi> thy <hi>Kingdom come;</hi> thy <hi>Will be done in Earth as 'tis in Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. —<hi>for</hi> thine <hi>is the Power and the Glory for ever.</hi> Amen. From this I obſerve: 1. That it is the Will of God, as declared by Chriſt, that the order we ſhould obſerve in our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions of God Almighty, and in pouring out our Deſires to him, is poſitively and directly to pray to God the <hi>Father,</hi> as the proper Appellation and Object of our Prayers. 2. That he that prays to God the Father, prays in that reſpect <hi>aright,</hi> and to the <hi>true</hi> God. 3. That it appears not that in our Prayers we are <hi>injoined</hi> to diſtinguiſh the Perſons, if we regard and eye by Faith the Being or Eſſence we worſhip: 1. Becauſe, if ſuch a thing as diſtinguiſhing the Perſons in Prayer were a Duty, or material, our Saviour would have inſerted it in his Directory, ſince he here gives an account of all the material Points of Prayer. 2. Becauſe on the contrary he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly injoins us to direct our Deſires (not to <hi>three,</hi> but) to <hi>one</hi> Perſon, even the <hi>Father;</hi> withal teaching us to uſe ſuch Expreſſions as are moſt proper to a <hi>ſingle Perſon, viz.</hi> three times
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:96824:13"/> 
                     <hi>thy,</hi> and once <hi>thine.</hi> 4. I obſerve that our Lord directs us to render and aſcribe ſuch Excellency, full Power, Soveraignty, Protection, Sacredneſs, Bounty, Clemency, Glory to the Father, as are only proper to be given to the <hi>whole</hi> and only <hi>Godhead;</hi> which ſtill ſhews that the proper glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Object of Divine Worſhip is the whole God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, as truly ſubſiſting <hi>all</hi> and <hi>whole</hi> in the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the <hi>Father,</hi> and under that Appellation to be worſhip'd. And as I have hitherto treated of poſitive Directions in this caſe, I ſhall briefly cite ſome Examples of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, as our Pattern to follow, whereby it may further appear moſt agreeable to Scripture to worſhip <hi>one</hi> Perſon. Firſt, Chriſt's Example, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.25. <hi>I thank</hi> thee, <hi>O</hi> Father, Lord <hi>of Heaven and Earth.</hi> Here he pays the duty of Thankfulneſs to the Father, and owns him as <hi>ſupreme</hi> Soveraign. Mark 14.36. <hi>And he ſaid, Abba,</hi> Father: <hi>all things are poſſible to</hi> thee, <hi>take away this Cup from me; nevertheleſs not as I will, but as</hi> thou <hi>wilt.</hi> Next I ſhall cite the Apoſtles: <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15. <hi>Ye have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Spirit of Adoption, whereby ye cry,</hi> Abba, <hi>Father.</hi> Rom. 15.6. <hi>That ye may with one Mind —glorify God, even the</hi> Father <hi>of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Gal. 4.6. <hi>God hath ſent forth the Spirit of his Son into your Hearts, crying,</hi> Abba, <hi>Father.</hi> The next Inſtance ſhall be the Adoration of <hi>Paul</hi> to this <hi>ſingle</hi> Perſon; <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.14. <hi>For this cauſe I bow my Knee to the</hi> Father <hi>of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Jam. 3.9. <hi>Therewith bleſs we God, even the</hi> Father. 1 Pet. 1.17. <hi>And if ye call on the</hi> Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And indeed it were tedious to cite all thoſe Texts that give Teſtimony to this thing. Theſe Gleanings are ſet down, that ye might believe that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Object of Divine Worſhip is the <hi>one</hi> moſt High God, as truly ſubſiſting <hi>all and whole</hi> in the Perſon of the <hi>Father:</hi> And believing it, that ye might direct your Adoration to him accordingly, and alſo have Charity towards all thoſe who have no other material fault but worſhipping the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> as the proper Object. Nay, methinks there is no Point of Divinity in the Holy Scriptures more clear than this thing, as any indifferent Eye may ſee: 'tis not a thing drawn from <hi>doubtful Conſequences;</hi> but plainly revealed, often repeated, and never contradicted, but confirmed by the univerſal Practice of the Prophets and Primitive Saints, and alſo by Chriſt and the Apoſtles; namely, That the moſt High is to be worſhipped as a ſingle <hi>impartible</hi> Eſſence, <hi>in one ſingle Perſon,</hi> without the Worſhippers being obliged at the ſame time to diſtinguiſh <hi>three</hi> diſtinct Subſiſtings and Deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations.</p>
                  <p>And on the other ſide, there is not <hi>one</hi> Inſtance to be given where any Man is recorded in the word of God, our <hi>only</hi> Rule and Guide, to adore the moſt High God under the apprehenſion of one Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in <hi>three</hi> Perſons; that is, I mean, did direct his Prayers or Thanks to <hi>three</hi> Perſons. And here I muſt take occaſion moderately to check ſome of my worthy and beloved Brethren, uſeful in the Miniſtry, who a little heated with an inordinate Zeal for the Doctrine of <hi>three</hi> Perſons in the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, fearing they may prejudice the Doctrine it ſelf by yielding too much to its oppoſite, do on the other ſide as much overſhoot the Mark, and form their Petitions quite beyond all Scripture-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction and Example. And tho no Examples, nor any thing like them can be given, yet they muſt conclude their Prayers, To thee, O Lord, <hi>Father, Son, and holy Spirit, three Perſons, one eternal God,</hi> be Honour, Glory, Praiſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> What ſhall one think of this, but that thoſe Men think if they ſhould not direct and form their Prayers to the Almighty <hi>better</hi> than <hi>Abraham, Jacob, Moſes,</hi> the Prophets of old, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Apoſtles did, their Prayers would be very <hi>defective,</hi> and not accompliſhed as they ought? Truly, to be zealous in a good thing is commendable; and that's a good thing for which we have <hi>Precept or Pattern:</hi> but for this there is neither. Now when we take the liberty to add to Divine Worſhip, however agreeable to our Opinions, and however well-meaning our Intentions may be, yet if our Device want Authority from ſacred Record, we mar in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of mending: for as there is a time for every Purpoſe, ſo is there a Rule for every Practice. God is the God of Order, and the ſupreme Giver of a Rule in all Inſtitutions and Worſhip: and when beyond the expreſs Rule, we ſhall foiſt in any Formality in Duty, we caſt Diſhonour on them of old, to wit, the Prophets and Apoſtles, yea Chriſt and God himſelf, as if he had been ſhort in giving ſufficient Rules, or Chriſt and his Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers ſhort in underſtanding him. And thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to mend, Formality, beyond Rule, or expreſs Precept or Example, has (as I hinted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) occaſioned all or moſt of the Innovations in Inſtitutions and Forms of Divine Worſhip: As for example, becauſe Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Except ye eat the Fleſh of the Son of God, and drink his Blood, ye have no Life in you;</hi> therefore as if perſons were bound to take more care for their Children than God himſelf directed, for many Ages they gave them the Lord's Supper, tho they had no expreſs Scripture for it. Likewiſe becauſe the Apoſtle
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:96824:13"/> ſays, <hi>Make melody to the Lord, and rejoice; and again I ſay, rejoice,</hi> and the like; therefore with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out rule ſome have invented Organs, as proper to heighten Rejoycings. Likewiſe becauſe the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Confeſs your Faults one to another;</hi> therefore the Roman Church hath invented Auri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Confeſſion. And truly tho I would be ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in compariſons, yet I would have all my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren ſee that it is <hi>dangerous</hi> to add <hi>Devices</hi> of our own; and that it is hardly ſufficient, becauſe the Scripture ſays, <hi>There are three that bear Record in Heaven, the Father, the Word, and the Holy Ghost, and theſe three are one;</hi> that <hi>therefore</hi> we muſt ſay in our Prayers, <hi>Father, Son, and Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, three Perſons, and one eternal God;</hi> when we have no precedent that ever any did ſo, who yet knew how to pray as well as we, having the firſt Fruits of the Spirit. And, as I ſaid before, were the diſtinction of Perſons in that one Eſſence as plainly diſcovered by Scripture and Reaſon, as the Oneneſs of that Godhead is (which yet I muſt confeſs it hardly is) yet the manner of our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions and our Expreſſions to, and Appellations of the Object of Worſhip in the Act of Worſhip, muſt depend upon God's <hi>Will,</hi> and Chriſt's <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,</hi> and not our <hi>own</hi> Device.</p>
                  <p>And now, according to my promiſe, concerning the Knowledg of the moſt High, and paying Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to him, I hope I have convincingly ſhewn the joint Agreement on all hands among the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties above-mentioned, and that at moſt there is but a circumſtantial difference between them; and no material one ſeems to be in their thoughts either concerning God or Worſhip unto him, both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving in the very <hi>ſame</hi> God that created the Heavens and Earth, the very <hi>ſame</hi> Eſſence all and whole, the very <hi>ſame</hi> that was and is the God of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> the <hi>ſame</hi> God and no other that is the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus, the very ſame God that Chriſt directs us to call Father, owning all his eſſential Properties, Power, and Prerogatives, each believing him to ſubſiſt all and <hi>whole</hi> in the perſon of the <hi>Father,</hi> and under that Appellation moſt <hi>proper</hi> to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped; only there is a little difference about this <hi>threefold</hi> manner of ſubſiſting, a thing (as has bin ſhewn) that God and Chriſt have at <hi>least</hi> been <hi>ſparing</hi> in declaring at any time, when he made diſcovery of himſelf in all Ages. And therefore I hope the Belief of it not to be look'd upon ſo <hi>binding,</hi> or the ignorance of it ſo <hi>damning,</hi> as to be <hi>the Test of Communion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And now, according to my promiſe, I ſhall come to ſpeak of the ſecond Perſon of the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>viz.</hi> the Chriſt of God.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Concerning the Chriſt of God.</head>
               <p>THIS Chapter containeth four Sections: Firſt, ſhewing that we are all agreed about the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Chriſt, who he is.</p>
               <p>The ſecond treateth of his Offices, therein alſo ſhewing that we are agreed.</p>
               <p>The third anſwers this Queſtion; Whether or no it be required, that in order to our right be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving in, and worſhipping of the Perſon of <hi>Jeſus</hi> of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> we muſt worſhip him as the moſt High God.</p>
               <p>The fourth treateth particularly of his human Nature.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect. I.</hi> Shewing that we are all agreed about the Perſon of Chriſt, who he is.</head>
                  <p>GReat have been the Miſtakes of many about the <hi>Perſon</hi> of the <hi>Meſſias.</hi> There ſeem to be in all Nations ſuch Sparks of Light as inform them they have need of ſome one to be their Friend to appeaſe Divine Wrath, and ſpeak to the moſt High for them; to which purpoſe the Jews adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to one <hi>Benchochab</hi> in the Reign of <hi>Adrian,</hi> who pretended to be the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> but came to nothing. Likewiſe in 1666, they followed one <hi>Sebaſtius Sevi:</hi> And after that one <hi>More</hi> pretending to be Chriſt, who both came to nothing. And they now look for a <hi>Meſſias</hi> to come, tho not <hi>Jeſus of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zareth.</hi> The Perſians rely on <hi>Haly,</hi> the Turks on <hi>Mahomet;</hi> and the Quakers ſay it is ſomething <hi>within, viz.</hi> a Spirit, or ſpiritual Subſtance. And
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:96824:14"/> there ſhall yet come (eſpecially in the laſt times) many Pretenders, calling themſelves Chriſts, which ſhall be found Liars.</p>
                  <p>But our Brethren and we all agree that he and no other, that was born of <hi>Mary,</hi> called <hi>Jeſus of Nazareth,</hi> nailed to the Croſs by the order of <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Pilat,</hi> in the days of <hi>Tiberius Ceſar;</hi> that he, I ſay, was, and is the <hi>Chriſt of God, the Saviour of the World.</hi> And why we ſhould cry out upon one another, that ſuch a one denies the true Chriſt, and believes in another Chriſt, I ſee no Reaſon, ſince we all agree that that one Perſon, born of <hi>Mary,</hi> was, and is the true Chriſt. 'Tis true, their Sentiments and ours may not be alike about his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, in his preexiſting before his Incarnation: but as that is a Myſtery hard for the Ignorant to underſtand, and Men of the greateſt Parts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly loſe themſelves in it; ſo I do not find the Apoſtles preſs it as material to be believed in, and underſtood: their main deſign ſeemed to be to prove, that he was the <hi>ſame</hi> Perſon the Prophets ſpake of; and to open the Power and Efficacy of his Death and Sufferings; but were very ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in talking of his preexiſting; which yet if it had been neceſſary to Salvation, it ſeems to me they would have opened it as well as other Points. But ſuppoſing our Brethren miſtaken in their Conceptions concerning Chriſt, what he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Incarnation; yet have they the ſame Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and Love for his Perſon as we have, believe him to be the <hi>very</hi> Chriſt of God as much as we, believe his Death to be available, and look upon him to be as ſufficient a <hi>Saviour</hi> as we do; and ſince they pitch on the very ſame Perſon that we do, I cannot think that they believe in a falſe, or <hi>another</hi> Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect. II.</hi> Concerning the Offices of Christ, ſhewing alſo that we are therein agreed.</head>
                  <p>HIS Name <hi>Jeſus</hi> ſignifies a Saviour, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> is in Engliſh, Anointed; ſo that this Perſon we ſpeak of, is the Anointed of God to ſave Mankind: His principal Office is to mediate between the <hi>moſt High offended,</hi> and the <hi>Lump of Men offending,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. Now concerning his Mediatorſhip, our Brethren and we agree, both believing that he is truly Man, having the Actions and Paſſions of Men, as eating, drinking, ſleeping, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And that he had a reaſonable Soul; that he is to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted our Prophet, Prieſt, and King; that his Death and Bloodſhed is ſufficient to ranſom the World; that there is no Remiſſion of Sins without him; that he now fits at the right hand of the moſt High; that he ſhall one day judg the Quick and Dead; that he has now all Authority in Heaven and Earth; that he is the true Son of God; that he is above the Angels; that his Fleſh is the true Heavenly Bread; that whoſoever eats thereof ſhall live for ever; that his Blood recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by Faith is Drink indeed; that he bare our Sins in his own Body on the Tree. In theſe things touching the <hi>Perſon and Offices of Chriſt,</hi> and in other material Points of like nature, there is an Agreement; and why there ſhould be ſuch a falling out, I cannot gueſs, unleſs thro Pride we will have all Men ſee as we ſee, and in ſuch things as ſeem not to be preached by the Apoſtles as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Sect. III.</hi> Treating on, and anſwering this Queſtion: Whether or no we are required, in order to our right believing in, and worſhipping of the Perſon of <hi>Jeſus</hi> of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> to worſhip him as the moſt High God?</head>
                  <p>BEfore I come directly to anſwer this Queſtion, I ſhall firſt ſpeak of the Worſhip and Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion due to him, as he is the Chriſt of God, and in <hi>that</hi> Capacity (to be ſure) <hi>ſubordinate</hi> and ſubject to the Father. Now I think it is on all hands al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, that Glory and Honour is to be given to Chriſt, as he is the Mediator. And the Reaſon why all Glory, and ſuch Honour is to be given to him, is, becauſe all Power in Heaven and in Earth is <hi>given</hi> to him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. Now I obſerve that Divine Honour is never to be given to the moſt High becauſe of a Power given him; for the moſt High gives all things, but no Power or Authority can be <hi>given</hi> to him; he has it all originally in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. Now the Power <hi>here</hi> ſpoken of, was a Power <hi>given</hi> unto him; therefore he had it <hi>not</hi> as moſt High, but as Chriſt, a confeſſed Subject, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it of the Father.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, it is ſaid, John 5.22, 23. <hi>For the Father judgeth no man, but hath committed all Judgment unto the Son, that all men ſhould honour the Son, even as they honour the Father.</hi> And verſ. 26. <hi>For as the Father hath Life in himſelf, ſo hath he given unto the Son to have Life in himſelf.</hi> From hence I note, that there is an Honour to be given to Chriſt, as to one
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:96824:14"/> inveſted with Power by and from another; and that God the Father hath given and beſtowed on him Power and Judgment, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on purpoſe that Men ſhould pay him this Honour.</p>
                  <p>And tho Compariſons, as we uſe to ſay, will not run on all four; yet for Illuſtration ſake I will inſtance the Caſe of <hi>Joſeph: Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> was King, yet ſays he to <hi>Joſeph,</hi> Gen. 41.40. <hi>Thou ſhalt be over my Houſe; and according unto thy Word ſhall all my People be ruled: ſee I have ſet thee over all the Land of</hi> Aegypt; <hi>and they cried before him, Bow the Knee.</hi> A Badg of Homage and Honour very probably given to the King when he rode a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the People.</p>
                  <p>Here you ſee, tho <hi>Pharaoh</hi> were King, yet the Execution of the Power, and the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Government is given unto <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph.</hi> So altho the Father, or the Moſt High, be he that hath Authority originally, yet the Honour of it, and the execution of it in Heaven and in Earth is given unto the Son, and he ſhall keep it and execute it until he hath ſubdued all his Enemies, and then ſhall deliver it up to God, even the Father: 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24, 25, 26, 27, 28. Now about this Honour and Power there is no Controverſy that I know of, every one of either Party granting that Chriſt hath not this Power and Honour, as he is eſſentially God moſt High, becauſe then he could not receive it, nor yet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver deliver it up again, as in all plainneſs he is ſaid to do. And this kind of Advancement, and Power, and Prerogative is intended, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.20, 21, 22. where it is ſaid, <hi>God hath ſet him far above all Principalities, and Powers, and Might, and Dominion, and every Name that is named, not only in this World, but alſo in that which is to come; and hath put all things under his Feet.</hi> The like is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned and intended, Phil. 2.9, 10, 11. <hi>Wherefore God alſo hath highly exalted him, and given him a Name which is above every Name: That at the Name of</hi> Jeſus <hi>every Knee ſhould bow, of things in Heaven, and things in Earth, and things under the Earth; and that every Tongue ſhould confeſs that Jeſus Chriſt is Lord, to the Glory of God the Father.</hi> The like alſo is intended <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5, 6, 7, 8, 9. and in many other places is this kind of Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity ſpoken of. But, as aforeſaid, this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is not controverted; but the Knot of the Queſtion is, Whether <hi>over and above</hi> this Honour, which is to be given unto him as Chriſt, and a principal Officer and Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative of the moſt High; I ſay, whether <hi>over and above</hi> this Honour we are not bound to worſhip him as the moſt High himſelf: that is, not as one deſerving Honour and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience becauſe of Dignity and Power given him, but as one deſerving and requiring it, having <hi>originally</hi> all Power and Dignity dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>eſſentially</hi> in him, and he the only ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Giver of it to others.</p>
                  <p>To this weighty Queſtion, with all Modeſty and Submiſſion to better Judgments (from whom, if occaſion be, I expect Information) I humbly anſwer, No; that ſuch Worſhip is not formally to be paid to the <hi>Perſon</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> as he is the Chriſt of God.</p>
                  <p>Miſtake me not; let none ſuppoſe that I hereby deny the Perſon of Chriſt to be eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially God: But I ſay, allowing that, yet it follows not from thence that we are to pay our Devotion to Chriſt as to the moſt High.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My Reaſons for it are as follows:</hi> Firſt, Becauſe when the Apoſtles preached and diſcovered him unto the World, they ſeem to diſcover and preach no ſuch Belief and Practice.</p>
                  <p>And firſt, for <hi>Peter</hi>'s firſt Sermon to the Multitude, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. which cauſed the Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the firſt Chriſtian Church: he preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es Salvation through the name of Chriſt, verſ. 21. he let them know that <hi>Jeſus</hi> of <hi>Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth</hi> was no Impoſtor, but a man approved of God by Miracles, Wonders, and Signs, ver. 22. he ſpeaks of his Death and Sufferings, ver. 23. his Reſurrection, v. 24. his Exaltati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ver. 33. and v. 36. concludes, <hi>Know aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly that God hath made the ſame Jeſus whom ye have crucified both Lord and Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here you ſee <hi>Peter</hi> omits no material thing: he ſpeaks of his Merits; They that call on him ſhall be ſaved: his Death, Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, Exaltation, receiving Empire and Honour; God hath made him Lord: but not one word of his being <hi>eſſentially</hi> God, and ſo on that account the Object of Divine
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:96824:15"/> Worſhip; which yet, had it been ſo mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial a Point as is now thought, did <hi>deſerve</hi> as much to be preached as any of the other. Likewiſe in his ſecond Sermon <hi>Acts</hi> 3. he preaches Chriſt from Verſ. 13. to the end; yet not one word of his being <hi>eſſentially</hi> the moſt High. The like i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to be obſerved in the fourth Chapter. Man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> places I might run over, but for brevity ſake I ſhall on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take notice of two more: one is where <hi>Peter</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſent to tell <hi>Cornelius</hi> what he ought to believe and do, <hi>Acts</hi> 10. v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rſ. 36. he lets <hi>Cornelius</hi> know that Jeſus wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Lord, as before he told the Jews, <hi>God had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ade him both Lord and Chriſt:</hi> He t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ls him that God had ſent the Meſſage of Peace by him, he tells him he was the Anointed of God; he tells him he was a Miracle-Worker, which ſhewed that God was with him: he tells him of his Death and Reſurrection: he teſtifies him to be the <hi>ſame</hi> the Prophets propheſied of to come: he preaches Remiſſion of Sins through Faith in his Name: he declares him to be ordained Judg of Quick and Dead; but not one word that he is to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped as eſſentially God Moſt High; which had it been a point of <hi>Faith,</hi> would ſurely have been told <hi>Cornelius</hi> and the Gentiles. Likewiſe when <hi>Paul</hi> informs the <hi>ignorant</hi> Athenians, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.31. after he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed the true God, he deſcribes Chriſt <hi>diſtinct</hi> from God as the <hi>ordained</hi> Judg of the World, but ſpeaks not of his <hi>Godhead.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>My ſecond Reaſon is, Becauſe as he is Chriſt he is <hi>diſtinguiſhed</hi> from God, and an Officer un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him: and therefore <hi>ſo as</hi> he is Chriſt to be believed in, ſaying of himſelf, his <hi>Father</hi> is <hi>greater</hi> than he, and than all, the Scriptures that direct us in our Faith in Chriſt, direct us to underſtand his <hi>Office;</hi> but ſeem to be ſilent concerning his <hi>Eſſence:</hi> Neither doth Chriſt any where <hi>require</hi> us to worſhip him as the moſt High; but we are to pray, to give thanks, and perform our Homage to the moſt High through Jeſus Chriſt, as the new and living way conſecrated for us.</p>
                  <p>But thirdly, <hi>nothing</hi> is Chriſt but what is <hi>anointed,</hi> (for Chriſt in plain Engliſh ſignifies <hi>anointed.</hi>) Now the Divine <hi>Eſſence</hi> was not anointed nor <hi>incarnate;</hi> for who ſhould <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint</hi> it, unleſs we will ſay the Divine <hi>Eſſence</hi> anointed the Divine <hi>Eſſence</hi> with the Divine <hi>Eſſence?</hi> Some will ſay that that is abſurd; and verily except we have a mind to fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the contradictory ridiculous Opinion of the Quakers, I think we can plead at moſt for no more than this, <hi>viz.</hi> that the ſecond Perſon of the Trinity was incarnate and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed, and not the Divine Eſſence it ſelf: And if ye will not believe me, believe Mr. <hi>Tho. Monck,</hi> in his Cure for the cankering Error, pag. 98. where he tells you, we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways diſtinguiſh betwixt the <hi>Eſſence</hi> of the Son and the Perſon; ſaying, the <hi>Eſſence</hi> is one with the Father, but not his <hi>Perſon:</hi> Therefore we ſay his Perſon was begotten, not his Eſſence; and we alſo ſay his Perſon took Fleſh of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> not his Eſſence; and therefore it was the <hi>Perſon</hi> of the <hi>Son</hi> that was born of her, not the <hi>Father,</hi> nor the Spirit; for tho the Eſſence of the three be one, yet the Perſons be diſtinct: and pag. 114. he reckons up the Abſurdities will elſe follow, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Father was he that took Man's Nature upon him, was tempted of the Devil, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered Hunger and Thirſt, was buffeted and ſcourged of the Jews, and put to death by wicked hands; is greater than himſelf, ſent himſelf into the World: he gave himſelf a Seat at his own Right Hand; he is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Image of himſelf, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Abſurdities he reckons up; theſe may ſuffice.</p>
                  <p>Now I humbly conceive Divine Homage and Adoration is to be given to the <hi>Eſſence</hi> of the moſt High, and not to a particular man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of its <hi>ſubſiſting;</hi> to wit, to a Perſon, which yet is all which is or was anointed (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Mr. <hi>Monck</hi>'s Opinion.)</p>
                  <p>But then I know it will be ſaid that each <hi>Perſon,</hi> and ſo the ſecond Perſon, contains in it all the <hi>Eſſence.</hi> Let it be ſo, I will allow that in the Perſon of <hi>Chriſt</hi> dwelt all the Fulneſs of the Godhead bodily, according to <hi>Col.</hi> 2.9. But then it muſt alſo be allowed that the Eſſence dwelt there as ſomething <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct</hi> from the Anointed, and not as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed it ſelf: It muſt alſo be allowed that the moſt High dwelt in Chriſt <hi>incognito,</hi> as ſome great Princes appear in foreign Courts
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:96824:15"/> and Places <hi>incognito,</hi> that is, tho they are perſonally preſent, yet they decline to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive thoſe Royal and Princely Honours due to their Character; receiving them only or chiefly in their Palace Royal. So tho the Almighty dwell in the Perſon of Chriſt, yet we are not taught to ſay, our Father who art in the <hi>Perſon of Chriſt,</hi> but our Father who art in <hi>Heaven;</hi> which Expreſſion he deſires we ſhould uſe while the Perſon of Chriſt was on Earth. And we have before ſhewn that we are to worſhip the Divine <hi>Eſſence,</hi> as ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting all and whole in the Perſon of the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> neither are we any where commanded or directed to ſay, our <hi>Son</hi> who art in Heaven, or our <hi>Spirit</hi> who art in Heaven, hallowed be thy Name; but only our <hi>Father.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſince the <hi>Divine Eſſence</hi> ſeems not to deſire us to worſhip him under the <hi>Denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> or in the <hi>Perſon</hi> of the <hi>Son,</hi> I think it ſafeſt for us to worſhip him as truly and wholly ſubſiſting in the Perſon of the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and under that Denomination.</p>
                  <p>Beſides, the Names of Son and Spirit, howſoever with reſpect of <hi>Eſſence</hi> they are believed to be God; yet I ſay theſe Names ſeem to diſtinguiſh them from God, and do denote them as Officers under God. Therefore it is ſaid the <hi>Father</hi> is greater than I, and than all: the Son knows not the Day and Hour of Judgment, but the Father only.</p>
                  <p>Likewiſe the <hi>Spirit</hi> when he comes, he ſhall not ſpeak of himſelf; but what he hears that ſhall he ſpeak.</p>
                  <p>From the whole I conclude, that the Chriſt of God ought in our Faith concerning him to be diſtinguiſhed from God himſelf; and that whatever may be ſaid of the Divine <hi>Eſſence</hi> dwelling in Chriſt, yet nothing was <hi>Chriſt</hi> but what was anointed; and that only the Perſon was anointed, or was incarnate, according to Mr. <hi>Monck</hi>'s Opinion.</p>
                  <p>And further, that whatever Divine <hi>Eſſence</hi> dwelt in Chriſt, or was Chriſt; yet the proper place to pay Adoration to it, is in the Perſon of the Father, and that he that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips the Father, worſhips all the Divine Eſſence under the proper Name and Appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation under which it ſhould be worſhipped, to wit that of the <hi>Father.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe things conſidered, I ſee no reaſon why we ſhould ſo ſtigmatize our Brethren, becauſe they worſhip the moſt High under the proper Name and Perſon that they ought; and do not uſe improper Names to do it by, as our <hi>Son</hi> who art in Heaven, or our <hi>Chriſt</hi> who art in Heaven, or our <hi>Spirit</hi> who art in Heaven; ſince thoſe Names or Perſons, whatſoever their Eſſence be, do not require us to worſhip the moſt High in them; but to underſtand and improve the Knowledg of their Office; and remember that that Perſon who was nailed to the Croſs, who cried out, My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me? was the Mediator betwixt God and us, the very Chriſt, the anointed, who did never require his Diſciples to worſhip him as the moſt High.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>SECT. IV.</hi> Treating particularly of his Human Nature.</head>
                  <p>AS touching the Contention about the <hi>human</hi> Nature of Chriſt, ſtrange it is to me, (and would have been ſtranger, had I not once dipped my Fingers in the ſame folly) that Men ſo well agreeing in the main ſubſtantial Points of the Faith of Chriſt, ſhould yet notwithſtanding ſo teaze one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther about a Circumſtance ſo dark as this is: They all believe that his Body was the true <hi>Son,</hi> and ſent of God, that he was a real Man, that he was a ſufficient Sacrifice and Saviour: But all this will not ſatisfy them, except they know what he was made of; yet the Scripture leaves it ſo, that if we make any determination, we muſt bring the plain Words to our meaning; for as it is ſaid, he
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:96824:16"/> was made of the Seed of <hi>David</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Fleſh, it is alſo as expreſly ſaid, the Word was made Fleſh, <hi>John</hi> 1.14. And <hi>Solomon</hi> the wiſeſt of Men, and the greateſt Searcher into Nature's Secrets that ever was, ſays, Who do know how the Bones do grow in the Womb of her that is with Child? ſpeaking of an ordinary Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>If an ordinary Conception be ſo dark then, much more this Conception of our Lord, which was beyond, and contrary to the Courſe of <hi>Nature:</hi> Therefore to make the Ignorance thereof ſo damning, and the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Knowledg of it the Teſt of Communion, ſeems to ſavour of <hi>Preſumption;</hi> and it is ſomething pleaſant to ſee old grave men diſcourſing ſo ſeriouſly and learnedly how far any Woman contributes towards any Child conceived in her; a thing ſo intricate, that the moſt famous Philoſophers have been at Daggers Draw about it: and when any man hath thought his Thought about it, he may be right, and he may be wrong, becauſe we are all left without light to travel in thoſe Paths.</p>
                  <p>For my part I intend not to follow them in this Diſcourſe or Controverſy, the whole appearing to me, and to many others, to be <hi>needleſs;</hi> ſince tho it muſt be granted that ſomebody is, and muſt needs be miſtaken, and under Miſapprehenſions in the caſe, yet the Miſtakes are not ſo <hi>pernicious</hi> to lead the miſtaken to queſtion whether this be the true Meſſias, promiſed to <hi>Adam,</hi> and all along propheſied of by the Prophets; but they, whoever they be, are very confident, as well as the other, that this is the true Chriſt; therefore pray why all this ſtir? this <hi>Jehu</hi>-like driving ſeems not to ſavour much of a true Chriſtian Spirit. But I ſhall conclude this Section with a Compariſon for illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my meaning, which I have here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore frequently made uſe of, ſometimes with good ſucceſs, in Diſcourſes of this kind.</p>
                  <p>We will imagine two Perſons, <hi>A</hi> and <hi>B,</hi> Servants to <hi>C,</hi> do grow refractory, and run away from <hi>C,</hi> and deſervedly in their rambles are taken by the Enemy, and made Slaves of in a foreign Land, help themſelves they cannot; but <hi>C</hi> hearing, and well underſtanding their Misfortune and Miſery, notwithſtanding their former Ingratitude, yet pities them, and ſends by a truſty hand a ſufficient Ranſom to redeem them, and obtain their Liberty.</p>
                  <p>The Ranſom arrives, and they are accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly redeemed, and preſently embark to go home to <hi>C;</hi> as they ſail homeward, (they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as well they may be, much affected with their Liberty) they are often diſcourſing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their Ranſom, they both agree, and queſtion not that it was none of their Deſerts, but the free Love and Bounty of <hi>C</hi> was the cauſe of the Ranſom's being ſent; neither do they queſtion in the leaſt whether or no it be come, or being come, whether it be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient; for in all this they are ſatisfied: But in their Diſcourſe it happens this Queſtion is dropt; that is Whether the Ranſom was Gold or Silver? <hi>A</hi> thinks he hath ſufficient Reaſons to believe it was Silver; and <hi>B</hi> thinks he hath as ſound Reaſons to believe it was Gold: they terribly inforce their Arguments on both ſides, and poſſibly neither of them both certainly know the truth of the matter, or have any infallible or certain Rule to know, yet they are both very confident; one ſays, he is ſure he is in the right, and he is ſure the other is in the wrong. And ſo after they have vexed and teaz'd one another more than enough, the Contention at laſt ariſes ſo high, that <hi>A</hi> will ſtay no longer in the ſame Ship with <hi>B,</hi> but will leave him, and ſail in ſome other Ship; nay ſtay, ſays <hi>B,</hi> do not leave me, ſince I love you, and we are agreed in the main things, and do find, thanks be to <hi>C,</hi> that the Ranſom was ſufficient; and why ſhould we part about this <hi>Circumſtance,</hi> eſpecially ſince we were both Partners in Slavery and Miſery, and were both made happy and ſet at liberty by this one Ranſom? and ſince we are both Strangers in this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, neither is there any in the Ship ſpeak the ſame Language that we do, let us en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the Comfort of each others Society, and be helpful one to another in Advice and Diſcourſe; who knows, being amongſt Strangers and Enemies, how we may need each others help? and conſider how com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:96824:16"/> it will be for us, that have been lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Friends and Companions and Fellow-Country-men, to talk together in our own Language, while thoſe Barbarians gabble in an unknown Tongue, and barbarous Language? Therefore pray do not leave me, but tarry with me. Ay ſays <hi>A,</hi> if you'l ſay as I ſay, and think as I think, that the Ranſom was Silver, I'll tarry with you then, and all ſhall be well; but if you will not ſay ſo, I am reſolved I'll be gone, I'll keep you company no longer, nor I'll regard nor take no more account of you than of one of thoſe Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Infidels from whence you come; nay you are full out as bad as they, or rather the worſt of the two; you deſerve, if you had your Deſert, to be <hi>curſed</hi> out of my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</p>
                  <p>Says <hi>B,</hi> theſe are hard Words, and ſo much the harder coming from one I ſo much eſteem, and for ſo ſmall an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: Howbeit, I am not by any of your Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments convinced that you are right; I cannot ſay as you ſay, I think ſtill the Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom was Gold; nevertheleſs, tho I think you are <hi>miſtaken,</hi> I can and will bear with you, pray ſhake hands, and be Friends, and bear with me; pray don't leave me, our parting will be very pernicious and uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, and thoſe Barbarians in the Ship will take n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tice of it, and check us with it, and every body will wonder at it; and which is worſt, <hi>C</hi> that ſent the Ranſom, and did us ſo much good, will know of it, and be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much offended with us: therefore pray be perſwaded to tar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y with me. No not I, ſays <hi>A,</hi> I am reſolved I'll be gone, and I'll print ſome Papers, and expoſe you, and I'll put a Bear's Skin upon you; and if I can, I'll make all them in the Ship believe that you are a Bear inde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d, and all the Dogs in the Ship ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l bark <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> you, that you ſhall have but little Comfort or Peace in your Voyage; and ſo in the mind I am in, I'll never come at you more, or bid you God ſpeed, and ſo adieu.</p>
                  <p>Away flings <hi>A</hi> in a great Heat, down ſits <hi>B,</hi> fetching a deep Sigh, and becomes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding melancholy, that he muſt ſail a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone. Now every body will be ready to think that this was a very untoward, ſcurvy, ſimple Trick of <hi>A,</hi> for ſo ſlight an occaſion to deal ſo with <hi>B,</hi> and leave him, thereby expoſing both himſelf and <hi>B</hi> to the odd Cenſure and Deriſion of the By-ſtanders. Yet what do ſome wiſe Men do leſs than the ſame thing?</p>
                  <p>While both Parties in this Controverſy were running from God, and taken captive under Sin and Wrath, and were unable to help themſelves, God ſaw and pitied their Condition, and freely ſends his Son to ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom and redeem them to the glorious Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the Sons of God; he accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly offers his Body, and redeems them from Sin and Wrath; they both without <hi>doubting</hi> do agree that contrary to their Deſerts God freely ſent his Son, and that <hi>Jeſus of Nazareth</hi> was he, and that he was a ſufficient Ranſom. But at the ſame time the Queſtion is dropt, what was that Body made of? ſays one Party, all that died on the Croſs to redeem us was originally a <hi>Creature of the Earth,</hi> of the Duſt of the Ground: No, ſays ſome of the other Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that which died for our Sins, tho it were a real and true <hi>natural</hi> Man, yet ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally was not of the Duſt of the Ground, nor a part of the <hi>polluted fallen Lump,</hi> but of a more noble Extract, to wit, the Lord from Heaven: And amongſt other things, it is ſaid they think ſo for this reaſon; becauſe if the moſt High could honourably with reſpect to his <hi>Juſtice,</hi> take any part of the fallen Lump, and ſanctify it, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of it without any Mediator or Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice offered for it; nay ſo accept of it not ony in its own behalf, but alſo as a Ranſom ſatisfactory for all the reſt of that Lump; then it will follow that there was no abſolute neceſſity for the ſatisfaction of Juſtice that there ſhould be any Mediator at all, ſince it appears that a part of that fallen Lump was accepted without any Mediator at all; but I'll not meddle with the <hi>Controverſy.</hi> In the mean time the other Party repreſented by <hi>A</hi> in our Similitude, ſay, except you ſay as we ſay, and think as we think, that that which died was of the Earth, we will leave you, and reject you as <hi>Hereticks:</hi> No ſays the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:96824:17"/> other Party repreſented by <hi>B,</hi> not ſo, we are your Brethren, we love you, pray don't part from us, we live in the love of Chriſt; we own the ſame Perſon to be Chriſt that you do; we believe him to be as ſufficient a Ranſom as you do; we believe him to be the Son of God as well as you, only we think in this matter you are miſtaken; yet we are willing to bear with you, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace you. If you leave us, God will be <hi>offended,</hi> good men <hi>grieved,</hi> young Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts <hi>ſtaggered,</hi> and the World will <hi>laugh</hi> at us, and ſcoff us. No, ſays the other Party repreſented by <hi>A,</hi> we will leave you, ſay what you will, you deſerve no Charity nor Indulgence, you ought to be <hi>excommunicated,</hi> if you had your due: We will expoſe you in printed Papers; we will perſwade every body, if we can, that you are Bugbears: we ſay you are no <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> you hold ſuch Hereſies as are ſufficient to corrupt all the Churches, and to root the Chriſtian Religion out of the World: You are worſe than the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and as bad as <hi>Atheiſts;</hi> nay you do deny the true God, and the Lord that bought you; you will bring on your ſelves ſwift Deſtruction; and therefore we will purge our ſelves of you, and ſo adieu.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lamentable</hi> it is, and to be bewailed, that they who ſhould ſtrive together for the Faith of the Goſpel, ſhould ſtrive to wound their Brethrens Reputation, repreſenting them as the worſt of Men: ſurely brotherly Compaſſion, and brotherly Communion, with a friendly and charitable Bearing, would be to the Goſpel much more adorning, in our ſelves much more becoming, and to our Brethren much more edifying. Let us live in the Love of God, and keep pure the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of Chriſt, leaving thoſe Myſteries till we ſhall know as we are known. There is one thing more I had almoſt ſlipt: ſome will ſay our Brethren own Chriſt to be the Son of God; but that ſignifies little, ſo long as they do not tell us how he is the Son of God. To which I anſwer, That it is unjuſt to condemn them for what we our ſelves are guilty of: for there is none of us all, while we tell them of Eternal Generation, that dare once open our Mouths to tell them how it is. And while they ſay Eternal Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration is againſt Reaſon, we ſay it is above Reaſon, and cannot be comprehended by Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. 'Tis true we tell them by the Pen of Mr. <hi>Monk,</hi> pag. 72. That the <hi>Perſon</hi> begets, and is begotten, but the <hi>Eſſence</hi> neither be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth, nor is begotten; and pag. 98. we ſay his <hi>Perſon</hi> was begotten, not his <hi>Eſſence.</hi> But ſome will ſay we have no Scripture ſays ſo; and do what we can, yet ſome young Converts, ignorant Perſons, and thoſe of mean apprehenſion, tho they may be honeſt-hearted Men and Women, yet in this caſe are ſo dull of hearing, that they<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l hardly ever underſtand it.</p>
                  <p>But enough of this. I ſhall now in the next place come to treat of the Holy Spirit, the third Perſon of the Holy Trinity.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Concerning the Holy Spirit.</head>
               <p>I Shall do little more in this Chapter, than tranſcribe what I have wrote on this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject almoſt ten years ago in a private Letter, which yet hath been made conſiderably pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick in <hi>Kent, London,</hi> and elſewhere; and having yet received no Anſwer to it, I ſhall tranſcribe ſo much of it as relates to the Controverſy concerning the Holy Spirit, <hi>viz.</hi> Herein I ſhall firſt conſider how far we are agreed in this alſo: There is none of you do queſtion whether this be he that moved upon the Waters in the Creation, or whether he be holy; or whether this be he that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended on our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>that that he declares and makes known the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Mind and Will of God or no; or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:96824:17"/> his Operations may be properly called the Works of God or no; or whether it be he that our Lord Jeſus Chriſt ſaid ſhould come or no; or whether his Aſſiſtance be helpful to mortify Sin, and perform Duties towards God with acceptance: nay, not only in this, but about all his Actions in the Saints, which I ſhall not ſtand in particular to name, both reſpecting the Manner, Matter, and Magnitude of them, I do think you both agree. So then ſtill the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fference lies here, whether he himſelf be the Eſſence of the moſt Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h from Eternity: a thing no where required to be known that I know of in the whole Book of God.</p>
               <p>But admit it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſo, that the Holy Spirit is in himſelf the moſt High God, then muſt it follow that he, as the moſt High, created the Heavens and the Earth, and ſo ſtill preſerveth the Creation: Then it follows that he that worſhips the moſt High God that created the Heavens and the Earth, and ſtill preſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ſame according to that Knowledg at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained of him in his Word; he, I ſay, then worſhips this Holy Spirit as much as he that particularly names him, altho in reſpect of his O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fice, he looks upon him differing from this moſt High God; and verily if we will heed the Scriptures, ſo we muſt all: for what he is in reſpect of his Eſſence, is not there expreſly declared; but as he is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted to us under the Notion of the Holy Spirit, he is declared to be different from the moſt High God, and therefore ſo to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved in, <hi>John</hi> 16.13. For there it is ſaid of him, <hi>That when he comes, he ſpeaks not of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but what he hears;</hi> ſure not from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but from another that he ſpeaks. From whence it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> plain, that in reſpect of his Office, which is the thing ſignified by the denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of <hi>[Holy Spirit]</hi> he is diſtinguiſhed from the moſt High God, and a Meſſenger ſent from him; and verily I think it highly neceſſary that every Chriſtian ſhould ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of him: for it is the Spirit that maketh unutterable Groans and Interceſſion for us unto the moſt High God, and not the moſt High that maketh Interceſſion to the moſt High. He then that believes in and of the Holy Spirit according to thoſe Articles where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you are agreed, I think his Faith in him is ſufficient and according to the Scriptures.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:96824:18"/>
            <head>
               <hi>AN APPENDIX, CONTAINING A Short REPLY to a Book Intitul'd,</hi> A Brief Inquiry whether they who aſſert, and they who deny the Divinity of our Lord Jeſus, may have Communion together at the Lord's Table, <hi>written by Mr.</hi> Joſeph Taylor.</head>
            <p>HAVING finiſhed the precedent Sheets before I ſaw Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi>'s Book, I could not therein take notice of it. Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> is one who for his Ingenuity I have long time highly eſteemed, tho we were never much perſonally acquainted. The reading his Book puts me in mind of what I mentioned in my Epiſtle to the Reader con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning thoſe little Buckets of Oil frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtarting forth from the Preſs upon us to increaſe and inflame our Contentions: and I cannot forbear comparing this to one of thoſe fiery Bombs charged with ſuch Matter, that in whatſoever Church it falls and fires, that Church is in danger of being rent and torn in pieces. I think every body ought to ſet to their hand, according to their abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, to prevent the fatal Conſequences of ſo miſchievous a thing.</p>
            <p>At firſt ſight I believed that a Reply there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to would be a very ſutable Appendix to my Book; but I ſhall be very brief, and not follow him into all particulars; partly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I would not ſwell this Piece too much, and partly becauſe I have heard that it is expected that a more full and diſtinct Reply will come from another hand.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I obſerve that Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi>'s main Arguments are originally <hi>French,</hi> and firſt appeared to the World in that Language: however, they are now adorned with an Engliſh Face and Tongue; and tho they were foreign by birth, yet they are now naturalized by the Act and Deed of an Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Hand and Pen. Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> confeſſes <hi>page</hi> 14. That he f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>llows Monſieur <hi>Abbadie</hi> in his <hi>French</hi> Treatiſe of the <hi>Divinity of our Lord:</hi> and I can aſſure you, that the manner and matter of Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi>'s chief Arguments ſtand ſo fair and orderly, and in ſome places almoſt <hi>verbatim</hi> in Monſieur <hi>Lamoth</hi>'s Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the <hi>Divinity,</hi> with the Texts of Scripture (as they ſtand in Mr. <hi>T</hi>'s Book) in their order cited and impr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ved, that at firſt ſight I began to think I had got another Impreſſion of Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi>'s Book in my hand. However, this Concluſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on I quickly came to, that one muſt needs, in great meaſure at leaſt, be the Father of the other; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Lamoth</hi>'s bears date 1693, I concluded that his was ſenior. However it be, I wiſh Mr. <hi>Taylor,</hi> e're he undertook this Task, had well conſidered that we had already but too many Engliſh Incendiaries; and therefore
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:96824:18"/> that there was the leſs need to call in thoſe French Refugees to help pull down the Peace of our Churches about our Ears.</p>
            <p>But to proceed, the deſign of Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi>'s Book, as he tells us, is to ſhew and evince that thoſe who aſſert, and they who deny that Chriſt is God, of the ſame Eſſence of his Father, ought not to have Communion together at the Table of the Lord. This he endeavours to demonſtrate from ten Reaſons ſo called.</p>
            <p>But firſt, I muſt own my Ignorance of Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi>'s meaning by that Expreſſion, which he often uſes [Chriſt is God of the <hi>Eſſence</hi> of his Father] by which I think he muſt mean one of theſe four things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That Chriſt's Divinity is an Eſſence flowing from, or begotten of the moſt High, the ſame in <hi>kind,</hi> tho diſtinct in <hi>number.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or ſecondly, That his Divinity is a <hi>part</hi> of the ſame Eſſence that is in the Father.</p>
            <p>Or thirdly, That his Divinity is <hi>all</hi> and <hi>whole</hi> of the Divine <hi>Eſſence</hi> it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Or fourthly, That he intends <hi>none</hi> of the Divine Eſſence, or eternal Being, neither in part nor whole, but only the <hi>ſecond Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If he means the firſt, that the Divinity of Chriſt is of the ſame kind with the Eſſence of the Father, but another diſtinct intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Being, and that this is alſo God moſt High; then this deſtroys the great Article of <hi>one</hi> Subſtance, wherein ſo joint an Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is: And God will then be no longer one, but unavoidably two intire, diſtinct, intelligent Beings; and ſo we ſhall have two Gods, two moſt Highs, two Almighties, two Alknowing ones: all which is nonſenſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the fourth degree, as well as untruth. But ſure he doth not intend ſo.</p>
            <p>Therefore, ſecondly, ſuppoſe he intends the ſame Eſſence of the Father for number, that is, a <hi>part</hi> of it; and ſo there is a part in the Father, and another part in the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n or Chriſt, which is Chriſt; but then this is to ove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>throw all our antient Creeds and Councils ſo much relied upon in this Caſe. <hi>Athanaſius</hi>'s Creed will be thwarted, which ſays, not <hi>dividing</hi> the Subſtance. Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> Mr. <hi>Wright,</hi> Mr. <hi>Preſton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Monk,</hi> the 39 Articles, which ſay <hi>without parts,</hi> will all come in againſt him: and, as I ſhewed before, if we divide the Eſſence, we muſt in our thoughts divide the eſſential Properties. But I do not think Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> will oppoſe himſelf to Reaſon, and ſo many famous Men and Creeds antient and modern, which will appear againſt him; and deny the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Simplicity and Unity of God into the bargain.</p>
            <p>But then, thirdly, if he means the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity of Chriſt is all and whole of the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſupream Being it ſelf; then it follows, that the whole Eſſence of God moſt High was incarnate, was anointed, was ſent from Heaven to do another's Will, became our Mediator; yea that the <hi>whole</hi> Eſſence of God had a <hi>Father,</hi> for Chriſt had a Father, not only as he was the Son of Man, but as he was the Son of God. This contradicts Mr. <hi>Monk,</hi> and I think moſt other Writers, who ſay, the <hi>Perſon,</hi> not the <hi>Eſſence,</hi> was incarnate and anointed: and indeed the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeems a little ſtrange; for who ſhould anoint it? with what ſhould it be anointed? who ſhould ſend it? who ſhould it mediate unto? Beſides, if all the Divine Eſſence be anointed, there is abſolutely as much ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of a Mediator betwixt us and Chriſt, as betwixt us and the Father, except it be ſaid that the Perſon of the Father only is offended. Now we know the Perſon of the Father is not the Eſſence it ſelf; for then Father muſt be anointed, and incarnate, and ſent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But he (the Father) is ſaid to be only a certain manner of the Divine Eſſence its ſubſiſting: And then we muſt ſuppoſe that the Divine Eſſence it ſelf was not ſo much, or at all offended; but only one of the Modes or Manners of its ſubſiſting. But this will be thought deep myſteries to Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntry people. My ſhort ſight cannot ſee how to av<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>id this, except we will ſay, that as the whole Divine Eſſence ſubſiſts in the Father, there it is ſupream, the giver of all things, Higheſt, and can do all things, the anointed, the offended: But as the ſame whole Divine Eſſence ſubſiſts in the Son, or Chriſt, it is diſtinct from the Father, it is ſent, was anointed, incarnate, a Subject, a
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:96824:19"/> Mediator, a Reconciler, could do nothing of it ſelf. I know not whether Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> will take this Courſe or no; but if he do, I am ſure he'll deſtroy the Notion that Chriſt is to be worſhipped as moſt High G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d: for if the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne Eſſence appear only ſupream in the Perſon of the Father, then in him (to wit, the Father) and under that name it is mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t proper t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be worſhipped; which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reeable to S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ripture. And as it is Chriſt, it is a diſtinct thing from God the Father; therefore as it is Chriſt, and ſo an O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>icer, we are to act Faith in what it doth, and not in what it is, ſince its eſſential Perfections appear ſupream only in the Perſon of the Father.</p>
            <p>But fourthly, ſuppoſe Mr. <hi>Tayl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r</hi> intends none of all theſe; and tho he over and over talks of Chriſt's being of the ſame E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſence of the Father, yet he intends nothing leſs; and that one Jot or Tittle, neither in whole nor part of the Divine Eſſence was incarnate, anointed, or was Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, but only the ſecond Perſon of the Trinity diſtinct fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m Eſſence (to wit, the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n.) And this indeed is Mr. <hi>Monk</hi>'s Opinion in his <hi>Cure for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ankering Err<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r,</hi> pag. 98. <q rend="margDblQuotes">We always diſtinguiſh between the Eſſence of the Son, and the Perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, ſaying the Eſſence is one with the Fath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, but <hi>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> his Perſon;</hi> theref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re we ſay, his <hi>Perſ n</hi> was begotten, not his <hi>Eſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>e:</hi> and we alſo ſay, his <hi>Perſon</hi> took Fle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> not hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</q> This alſo ſeems to be the Opinion of many other Authors, although I have not now opportunity to ſearch and quote them. But if this indeed ſhould be his O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inely is he catch'd then? for they that have received his Book for Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox and good proof, are taught to bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eve that ſuch Perſons as de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, or do not believe that Chriſt is eſſentially God, are to be mark'd out for Excommunication and Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Now if Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> believes that the Divine Eſſence, neither whole nor part, j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t or tittle, was incarnate, anointed, or was Chriſt, but only the Perſon, then he muſt needs be one of them appointed f r De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruction and Excommunication, and ſo his fiery Bolt is returned into his own Boſom.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe this indeed ſhould be his meaning, that only the ſecond Perſon (as I think moſt believe) was in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arnate and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, then by Perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n he intends either an int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lligent Bein<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, Mind, or Spirit diſtinct from the one Eſſence, and the other two Perſons; or elſe he intends only a certain Manner or M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de of ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſting of the one intelligent Being. If he intends the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, he muſt b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lieve three or four diſtinct intelligent Bei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, Min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, or Spirit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, in God; and I think t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t will be three or four Gods.</p>
            <p>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t I could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ford <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lmoſt to paſs my word for Mr. <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ylor,</hi> that he doth not intend ſo: Therefore I rather take him in the latter ſenſe, to wit, a Mode or Manner of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting diſtinct from Eſſence. If ſo, then it will ſtill follow that Chriſt is not to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped as eſſentially God moſt High; for then he is n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t the Eſſence, but only a Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner or M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de of it. And I have before pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ved divine W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſhip, as to the moſt High, is to be given to the Divine Eſſence it ſelf, and n t directly and formally to any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Manner or Mode of it.</p>
            <p>I mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ht ſpeak more to this, but I fear I have ſaid ſo much already, that ſome igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant People will be ready to think we Trinita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, at leaſt ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me of us, hold ſtrange and nice Notions of Chriſt: Nay, perhaps they will ſay that we hold that Chriſt, as to his human Nature, or Manhood, is no Perſon, but a Nature only; and as to his Perſon is not Eſſence or Subſtance, but only a certain Manner or Mode of Eſſence: But enough of this. When all's done, I cannot tell which is Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi>'s meaning; and therefore I hereby pray him, if he appears in print a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, to e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in himſelf more diſtinctly and directly in this caſe.</p>
            <p>I now come to conſider his Reaſons. His firſt Reaſon why ſuch as believe, and ſuch as disbelieve Chriſt to be of the Eſſence of his Father, ought not to have Communion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether at the Table of the Lord, is, That either they that believe it, or thoſe that disbelieve it, muſt needs be Idolaters, and they muſt eſteem each other either guilty of Blaſphemy or Id latry. To which I return theſe following Repl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:96824:19"/>
            <p>Firſt, I miſlike the faſhion of this Reaſon.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I do not approve the Expreſſions of Idolatry and Blaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hemy, being too groſs to be beſtown ſo li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erally on Perſons ſo nearly united in the Faith of the true God, and the true Chriſt and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is Laws, as I have in the foregoing ſheets ſhewn they are. Milder Conſtructions and Expreſſions better become the Cauſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This manner of arguing ſeems to me too deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erate. Mr. <hi>Tay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r</hi> takes this Weap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n point<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d at both end<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and ventures to ſet one point at his own Breaſt, truſting in the ſtren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kin of his own Cauſe, and ſo makes a thruſt at his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thren.</p>
            <p>Altho Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> be a fallible Man, yet he is ſo con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>dent that his Conceptions are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly right in this confeſſed Myſtery and Controverſy, that hath puzled the moſt learned Men in all Ages (and ſadly divides them at this time) that he ventures to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim it to the World, that in caſe he be miſtaken, he is an Idolater, and leaves him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſo upon Record to Poſterity. I have heard of ſome who would hazard the loſs of one of their Eyes, rather than their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours ſhould enjoy both theirs: Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> will run the hazard of being accounted an Idolater, in caſe he be in the wrong, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than his differing Brethren ſhall go without the Imputation of Idolaters and Blaſphemers.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſee no ground for that Clauſe in his Reaſon, <hi>viz.</hi> That they that disbelieve Chriſt to be eſſentially God, are Idolaters. I take Idolatry to be giving Divine Adoration and Worſhip to any Object, as if he were the moſt High God, when it is not the moſt High God.</p>
            <p>Now theſe Unitarians that do not believe Chriſt to be eſſentially God moſt High, do not worſhip him as ſuch, but as one receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Power and Authority from another. But if Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> be of the opinion that it is Idolatry, for any Reaſon, to give Worſhip and Honour to any Creature (as he ſeems to ſay pag. 23.) therein I diſſent from him: for altho to worſhip any Creature as the moſt High when God allows it not (that is, when it doth not immediately repreſent him) be Idolatry, yet when Creatures ſhall and do immediately repreſent God m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt High, and receive Authority from him, I ſee not but we may without Idolatry worſhip them: for elſe firſt we ſhall in a manner impute I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry to <hi>Abraham, Moſes, David, John,</hi> and others; f r I remember <hi>Abraham</hi> bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d his Head, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the three Angels came to him, and ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> interceſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne of them for <hi>Sodom,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing him the Deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of <hi>my L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rd:</hi> I ſuppoſe n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> body thinks this Angel was eſſentially God; for then <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raham</hi> could not have ſeen him. Likewiſe <hi>Moſes</hi> is comma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ded to pull off his Shoes in honour to the a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pearance of God by his Angel in the Buſh. Likewiſe <hi>David</hi> fell on his Face to the ground bef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, and ſeems to direct his Prayer unto him, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21.10, 17. Likewiſe <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> gives the Denomination of <hi>Lord</hi> to the <hi>Angel, Acts</hi> 10.4. Likewiſe <hi>John</hi> the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine falls at the Angel's Feet, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.17. for tho the Revelation was Chriſt's, which God gave him, yet the diſcovery to <hi>John</hi> was made by the Angel, Chap. 1.1.</p>
            <p>But again, Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> allows himſelf and others to worſhip a Creature without the imputation of Idolatry, namely the human Nature of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>which, in his own O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, is a Creature only;</hi> yet it was worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped when it was on Earth, and Men beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged Mercy of it: It is and ought to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped now, and ſhall be worſhipped here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            <p>But if Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> reply, that this is for this particular reaſon, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe it is perſonally joined unto the Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine Nature, and therefore is not a Creature only.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, 1ſt, That if we may, for any Reaſon, give worſhip to a Creature without being Idolaters; then at leaſt his firſt Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion is not univerſally true, <hi>viz.</hi> That to worſhip any Creature is Idolatry.</p>
            <p>But 2ly, Suppoſe what Union you will in an orth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dox Senſe, yet the Divine Nature is no part of the human Nature, nor the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man any part of the Divine Nature, but they are really diſtinct; therefore the human Nature, and every part thereof, is a Creature only.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:96824:20"/>
            <p>And 3ly, Holy Scripture, if you'l believe and heed that, doth not any where ſay that we are to worſhip the Man Chriſt, becauſe it is perſonallly joined to the Divine Nature; but the Reaſon given why we ſhould wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip it, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, becauſe it hath <hi>received,</hi> and God hath <hi>given</hi> and <hi>committed</hi> unto it Power, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and Judgment: The principal Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for ſo doing is, that all men ſhould ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the Son as they honour the Father. Likewiſe <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.9, 10. Wherefore <hi>God hath highly exalted him, and</hi> given <hi>him a Name, which is above every Name, that at the Name of Jeſus every Knee ſhould bow, both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f things in Heaven, and things in Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But thirdly; I further reply to M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Taylor</hi>'s firſt Reaſon, That altho, in caſe he be miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, he hath wilfully thruſt himſelf into the numb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r of Idolaters, and theref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves but little p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty; yet out of Charity I will help him a little, and ende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>our to ſhew him that tho he ſhould be m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ken, yet he is no Idolater, nor y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t the othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>My reaſon f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r it is this; He dir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Adoration and Worſhip to the whole Divine Eternal Being, that created all things, the true God, allowing alſo in him all the eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Attributes. Now he that worſhips the true God, cannot be an Idolater.</p>
            <p>It is true, if Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> be miſtaken, he i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in an Error, becauſe he worſhips this Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in the wrong place, to wit, in the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Chriſt, when it ſhould be in the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Father only in Heaven: but ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill it is the ſame Eſſence, he intends that and no other than he who i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the God of <hi>Abraham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And on the other hand; if the Unitarians be miſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ken, yet they intend to worſhip the ſame Eſſence all and whole, and no other; they bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eve it t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be in the Perſon of Chriſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut not to be an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inted. They conceive it t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be an intire Being ſubſiſting in the Father, yet ſtill the very Eſſence that we worſhip, and no other: Therefore neither can they be Idolaters. I will conclude my Anſwer to this firſt Reaſon with this Argument.</p>
            <p>They that worſhip all and whole of the Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine Eſſence of the Eternal and Supream bein<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, who is the true God, are not therein, nor cannot be Idolaters or Blaſphemers. But both Trinitarians and Unitarians worſhip all and whole of the ſame Divine Eſſence of the Eternal and Supream Being, who <hi>is the true God: Ergo,</hi> neither Trinitarians nor Unitarians are Idolaters or Blaſphemers.</p>
            <p>Thus I hope his firſt Reaſon is mortally wounded.</p>
            <p>His ſecond Reaſon is, pag. 5. <hi>Becauſe they that deny Chriſt is eſſentially God moſt High, deny the Perſon of the Son of God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon deny the true Chriſt, and bring another in his ſtead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He endeavours to prove this bold Aſſertion thus: If the Perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n of Chriſt conſiſt both of a divine and human Nature, which is the whole of his Perſon, then they who deny both Natures in Chriſt, deny the whole of his P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſ n.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, firſt, I utterly deny, and Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> cannot prove, that any of our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren diſown both Natures in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, as hath been ſhewn, Mr. <hi>Tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor</hi> ought to have ſhewed what he intended by Divine Nature, whether the Eſſence of God in kind, in part, or in whole; or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther none of it, but a Perſon only.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I have heard ſome ſay that the human Nature was no part of the Perſon of Chriſt: And they ſeem to argue not without Reaſon; for, ſay they, if the ſecond Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nity be God, then it was a perfect and compleat Perſon before its aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming Fleſh: for whatever is, or is in God, is perfect and compleat to a tittle; now that which is perfect and compleat, can have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing added to it without making it imperfect, as a Yard or Ell that is exact and perfect in meaſure can have nothing in the leaſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure added to its length, but you make it thereby imperfect. Therefore though it be believed that human Nature was joined to this Perſon, yet it was no part of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi>'s ſuppoſition that Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt's Perſon conſiſteth of a divi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e and human Nature, cannot be true.</p>
            <p>But, Fourthly, Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> doth but ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that Chriſt's Perſon conſiſteth of divine Nature or Eſſence, he doth not here offer to prove it: Now tho it ſhould be true, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:96824:20"/> granted that others have proved it; and tho it be ſuppoſed that he can prove it, yet till he has proved it, it is but begging the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And therefore I need here ſay no more to it.</p>
            <p>But, Fifthly, Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> improves this Reaſon, <hi>p.</hi> 6. thus: <hi>If they that deny what is eſſential to his Godhead may be ſaid to deny God, then they may be ſaid to deny Chriſt, who deny what is eſſential to his Perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whatever may be ſaid to this, I will not now quarrel with it; I think I can give it him, and yet not hurt my Cauſe. But my eye is upon another Aſſertion, <hi>p.</hi> 7. derived from this: <hi>The divine Nature is eſſential to the Perſon of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, <hi>Firſt,</hi> (as to the former) Till this Aſſertion be proved, the Queſtion is but begg'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I do not ſee the Conſequences of this Argument. I confeſs they who deny that Chriſt received Power from God, deny his Authority; they that deny him to be anointed of God, deny him to be the Chriſt of God; they who deny him to be Chriſt who was born of <hi>Mary,</hi> deny the true Perſon of Chriſt: but how they who deny him to be the Eſſence of God, deny his Perſon, I veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do not ſee; unleſs Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> had firſt ſaid and proved, that Chriſt could not be a Perſon except he were eſſentially God, or which is all one, that to be of the Eſſence of God, is an eſſential Property of a Perſon. But I do not think that this can be thought or proved to be the neceſſary Part of a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; for then no <hi>Man</hi> can be a <hi>Perſon</hi> except he be of the divine Eſſence. I conceive, if any Man ſhould deny that Chriſt had a Mind, a Soul, a Life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he would indeed deny the Perſon of Chriſt, becauſe he denys him to have or to be <hi>that</hi> without which it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to be a Perſon. But to deny Chriſt to be a Perſon, except he be eſſentially God, is ſtrange Logick to me, and I doubt not to moſt conſidering Men. Now the Unitarians, at leaſt thoſe whom I mainly vindicate, do believe that Chriſt had all that needed to make him a compleat Perſon, as Life, Soul, Mind, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They alſo believe that this Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon was anointed of God, which is ſufficient to make him a compleat Chriſt; and they are right in all, and deny none of his Offices. I'll conclude my Anſwer to this Reaſon with this Argument: They that believe that Jeſus of <hi>Nazareth</hi> had all that was ſufficient to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him a compleat Perſon, and a compleat Chriſt, cannot truly be ſaid to deny the true Perſon of the true Chriſt. But the Unitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans believe that Jeſus of <hi>Nazareth</hi> had all that was ſufficient to make him a compleat Perſon and a compleat Chriſt. Therefore the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians cannot truly be ſaid to deny the true Perſon of the true Chriſt. Thus this Reaſon lies a bleeding.</p>
            <p>But his third Reaſon is, <hi>p.</hi> 10. <hi>Becauſe that a Man cannot be ſaid to be a true Believer in Jeſus Chriſt, that denys Chriſt to be of the Eſſence of his Father.</hi> And his ground for this Reaſon is this, <hi>Becauſe there can be no Act of Faith without the true Object of Faith.</hi> This latter Aſſertion I can grant him.</p>
            <p>Now the true Object of Faith in this caſe is Jeſus of <hi>Nazareth;</hi> but, quite contrary to Mr. <hi>Taylor,</hi> I argue: If the Unitarians have the true Object of Faith, then they are in that Particular true Believers in Chriſt; but they have the true Object of Faith, <hi>Ergo</hi> they are true Believers in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>I prove the <hi>minor</hi> thus: If Jeſus of <hi>Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth</hi> be the true Object, and they believe in him, then they have the true Object of Faith: But Jeſus of <hi>Nazareth</hi> is the true Object of Faith, and they believe in him; therefore they (the Unitarians) have the true Object of Faith.</p>
            <p>But if Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> intends by having the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Faith, that none can have a true Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Faith, except they underſtand and know the true Nature and Matter thereof, and whereof it conſiſteth; then I confeſs I am wholly of another Mind from him: for at that rate we can have no Object of Faith, becauſe we are utterly ignorant of the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Nature of any Thing or Subſtance. Muſt not <hi>Iſrael</hi> believe that the <hi>Manna</hi> was ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Food, becauſe they knew not the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, or the Nature of it? Muſt not I believe that there is a Sun, becauſe I am ignorant from what that glorious Orb was produced? Neither do we know its Nature; nay, we know not the Nature of any Being, tho ſuch
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:96824:21"/> as we daily converſe with. 'Tis much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted by ſome of the greateſt Searchers into Nature's Secrets, whether the Fire be Light or Heat, or whether it be either or neither of them both. Muſt not I believe I have a Soul, tho ignorant of its Subſtance? Neither do I certainly know its Original, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther produced by natural Generation or Infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Muſt not I believe there is a Wind, tho I know not its Subſtance or Matter? To conclude, In the ſame hour I was writing this, I caſt my eye on Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Doctrine of the Trinity; and in <hi>page</hi> 7. I found theſe words; <q rend="margDblQuotes">It is ſo far from being a wonder to meet with any thing we do not perfectly underſtand, that I know nothing in the world which we do perfectly underſtand: it is agreed by all Men, who ever conſidered this Matter, that the <hi>Eſſence</hi> of things cannot be known, but only their Properties and Qualities.</q> Thus far Dr. <hi>Sherlock.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi>'s fourth Reaſon is in <hi>page</hi> 11. <hi>Becauſe they that deny Chriſt to be the Eſſence of God, deny the Lord that bought them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Reaſon ſtanding on the ſame bottom with the former, the ſame Anſwer may ſuffice.</p>
            <p>His ſixth Reaſon (for he hath no fifth that I can find) is: <hi>This Principle of Chriſt's being the Eſſence of God, is the Rock upon which Chriſt hath built his Church.</hi> For proof of which he cites <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.15. where <hi>Peter</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, <hi>Thou art Chriſt the Son of the living God:</hi> And our Lord ſaith, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this Rock will I build my Church.</hi> But the neceſſary Conſequence of Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi>'s Reaſon or Proof is ſo far off, that my dull Genius will not reach it: I will put it into the form of an Argument.</p>
            <p>To be a Son of God, is to be the Eſſence of God: But Chriſt owns that he is the Son of God; <hi>Ergo,</hi> He owns he is the Eſſence of God.</p>
            <p>But then perhaps ſome unhappy Brain or other will ſay, At that rate of Reaſoning one may prove <hi>Adam,</hi> Angels and Saints to be all the very Eſſence of God; for they are all called Sons of God. I ſpeak not this as ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing that Chriſt is the Son of God in no other Senſe than <hi>Adam,</hi> Angels, and Saints are; but to ſhew how ſhort Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi>'s Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing comes of what he intends it for.</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> ſaith, <hi>page</hi> 13. <hi>Except by the word</hi> Son of God, <hi>we underſtand one and the ſame thing, it is impoſſible we ſhould have one and the ſame Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If this be true, ſetting the Unitarians a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, there are not many of us Trinitarians have one and the ſame Faith: for ſome by <hi>Son of God</hi> intend a diſtinct intelligent Being and Mind from Father and Spirit, as Dr. <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock.</hi> Some ſay, it is only a Mode of the divine Eſſence, but not the divine Eſſence it ſelf, as Mr. <hi>Monk.</hi> Some in effect ſay, it is called a Perſon, but indeed in a proper Senſe is not; and that therefore it is a Somewhat, as Dr. <hi>Wallis.</hi> Some ſay, it is a Quality and Property of the divine Eſſence. Some ſay, it is the Eſſence it ſelf. The School-men ſay, it is God knowing himſelf by a reflex Act. Thus you ſee we are all to pieces a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our ſelves; and when we are united, and underſtand by <hi>the Son of God</hi> one and the ſame thing, 'tis like the Unitarians will fall in with us.</p>
            <p>But alas, alas! now am I come to the kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Reaſon of all Reaſons, to wit the ſeventh, <hi>page</hi> 13. if I can but diſpatch it, I ſhall think my Work near done; it is this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Doctrine of Chriſt his being the Eſſence of God, is a Principle of that Conſequence, that the Chriſtian Religion ſtands or falls with it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To demonſtrate this, Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> lays down theſe two fearful and monſtrous Poſitions, namely: <hi>That if Jeſus Chriſt be not true God, of the ſame Eſſence with his Father; it follows, firſt, that the Mahometan Religion is prefera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Chriſtian, and</hi> Mahomet <hi>was a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Prophet than</hi> Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, That Chriſt was an Impoſtor and Deceiver; the Jews did juſtly in ſentencing him to Death for Blaſphemy: That the Chriſtian Religion is Idolatry and Superſtition, and the Meſſias is not yet come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This roaring Reaſon makes a terrible Noiſe in Country Churches. If this be true, 'twere enough to make a Man afraid to come near a
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:96824:21"/> Unitarian as long as one lives. Unitarians did I ſay? nay, Mercy, Mercy; for as to ſeveral of our leading Trinitarians, what will become of them? for Mr. <hi>Monk</hi> plainly denies that Chriſt is the Eſſence of God, but only a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or Mode. Dr. <hi>Wallis</hi> is of the ſame Mind; and I am almoſt afraid Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> is leaning that way; and if he ſhould, what a lamentable thing would that be!</p>
            <p>But now by way of Reply: Firſt, obſerve that this Expreſſion, <hi>Chriſt of the Eſſence of his Father,</hi> is not directly in expreſs terms taught us by our Lord, or the holy Scripture. Secondly, That our Proofs are only Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, a long time ago, and ſtill much controverted by very learned Men; and yet Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> adventures to be ſo confident as to ſay in effect, that ſuppoſing his Opinion be not true, that is, if he be miſtaken, then Chriſt muſt needs be beneath <hi>Mahomet,</hi> nay an Impoſtor, and the Jews did well to put him to Death for Blaſphemy.</p>
            <p>Theſe are very high Words, and look too bold and preſumptuous. I confeſs if the Pope and Church of <hi>Rome</hi> had ſaid ſo, it had been no very ſurpriſing thing; becauſe they believing themſelves infallible, might there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore look upon their Interpretation of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, even in the moſt nice and dubious Points, to be certainly and infallibly true; for infallible Perſons cannot err.</p>
            <p>But for Mr. <hi>Taylor,</hi> who (I doubt not) thinks himſelf a fallible Man; for him, I ſay, to hug and magnify his own Opinion in ſo intricate and curious a Queſtion, wherein (as hath been hinted) the moſt learned Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians are greatly divided in their Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and to value it at ſuch a rate as to think and proclaim that either his Notion muſt be true, or Chriſt muſt be falſe, this is very amazing. And I cannot forbear thinking that Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> had Monſieur <hi>Lamoth</hi>'s Book by him, when he penn'd this Reaſon. <hi>Lamoth</hi> in his Diſcourſe of the Trinity, <hi>p.</hi> 15. hath theſe Expreſſions; <q rend="margDblQuotes">That in caſe the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Trinity, as now held, be not true, then the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> had not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Senſe, nor any tolerable degree of Underſtanding, nay was a Mad-man; and the reſt of the Apoſtles were Blaſphemers. And <hi>page</hi> 33. I make no difficulty (ſaith he) to ſay, they have deceived us moſt ſhamefully, and their Writings are no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than continual Blaſphemy if Chriſt be not God.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But, Secondly, I ſhall endeavour to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate, that in caſe Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> ſhould be miſtaken, and Chriſt be ſuppoſed not to be of the Eſſence of God, yet it doth not thence follow (notwithſtanding all Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> ſays) that he was worſe than <hi>Mahomet,</hi> or that the Chriſtian Religion is worſe than <hi>Mahometiſm:</hi> To which purpoſe I will conſider what he ſays.</p>
            <p>His chief, if not only Reaſon for this, is in <hi>page</hi> 15. <hi>Becauſe the Chriſtian Religion brings in Idolatry, but</hi> Mahomet <hi>aboliſhes it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, I ſhall not concern my ſelf with <hi>Mahometiſm,</hi> nor magnify it for expelling I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry: But for the Chriſtian Religion, that it brings in Idolatry in the caſe ſuppoſed, I deny; for if the Chriſtian Religion neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily brings in Idolatry, it muſt be either in the Unitarians or the Trinitarians: But it doth not neceſſarily bring in Idolatry in the Unitarians, nor yet in the Trinitarians; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Chriſtian Religion doth not neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily bring in Idolatry.</p>
            <p>To make ſhort; for proof of the <hi>minor,</hi> I refer you to the cloſe of my Anſwer to his firſt Reaſon.</p>
            <p>I come now to his ſecond monſtrous Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, namely, <hi>If Chriſt be not the Eſſence of God, then he is an Impoſtor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the conſequence of this I deny, and on the contrary affirm, that tho Chriſt were not of the Eſſence of the moſt High, yet he is no Impoſtor; which I prove by this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>If Chriſt did never affirm himſelf to be the Eſſence of God, nor compel any Body ſo to believe; then tho he ſhould not be ſo, yet in this he is no Impoſtor. But Chriſt did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver affirm himſelf to be the Eſſence of God, nor compel or command any Body ſo to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve: <hi>Ergo,</hi> Altho he ſhould not be ſo, yet in this caſe he was no Impoſtor.</p>
            <p>The <hi>minor</hi> I thus prove:</p>
            <p>If Chriſt did ever affirm himſelf to be the Eſſence of God moſt High, or command any
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:96824:22"/> Body ſo to believe; then Mr. <hi>Taylor,</hi> or ſome body elſe, can ſhew us where or when he did ſo. But Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> nor no body elſe can ſhew us where or when he did ſo: <hi>Ergo,</hi> Chriſt did never affirm himſelf to be the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God.</p>
            <p>In Argumentation that which appears not is not: when an Inſtance is given that Chriſt did ſo, then my Argument muſt fall to the ground.</p>
            <p>And it is remarkable that when the Jews charged him, that he being a Man made himſelf God, <hi>John</hi> 10.33. after he had told them that Men in their Law had been called Gods, ſaith he, <hi>ver.</hi> 36. <hi>Say ye of him that the Father hath ſanctified, and ſent into the World, Thou blaſphemeſt, becauſe I ſaid I am the Son of God?</hi> From whence I obſerve, that whatever the Eſſence of Chriſt is, yet he as Chriſt did not oblige any Body to believe that he was of the Eſſence of God; for he doth not here plead or anſwer: Say ye of him who is the <hi>Eſſence of God?</hi> but him whom the <hi>Father</hi> hath <hi>ſent.</hi> So that the Eſſence of God is not only not expreſſed, but utterly hidden and excluded in this Anſwer, for that Eſſence can be ſent by none.</p>
            <p>In the next place; As Chriſt hath not any where that I know of required us to believe him to be the Eſſence of God, ſo neither doth Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> prove him to be ſo.</p>
            <p>To prevent Miſtakes, take notice, as I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did, ſo I do not now deny that Chriſt is eſſentially God: it is a great and deep Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy. But I ſay, whatever others have done, or Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> can do, he in this Book, I humbly conceive, hath not done it; and till he has done, he begs the Queſtion. I will ſcan his Proofs, tho it had been better for another, than I who am a Trinitarian, to have done it. Another Inconveniency alſo attends me, <hi>viz.</hi> I have not room enough, but am conſtrained only to touch at things: However, in ſhort I will hint at the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable things I obſerve, and not ſtand to ſpeak to all Particulars.</p>
            <p>His firſt Eſſay is <hi>page</hi> 24. <hi>Becauſe the Names of God are applied to Chriſt.</hi> Firſt, I anſwer, That thoſe who read impartially thoſe Texts he cites, may find that ſeveral of them ſpeak particularly of God the Father. Secondly, It doth not neceſſarily follow, becauſe the Name of God is ſometimes given to Chriſt, that therefore he is eſſentially God moſt High; for the Name of God hath been given to Men, to <hi>Moſes,</hi> to <hi>Solomon,</hi> and divers chief Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he ſays <hi>page</hi> 25. <hi>That the incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable Names of God are given him, namely,</hi> Jehovah, <hi>and</hi> I Am. I anſwer, both theſe Names have alſo been applied to Angels, <hi>Zech.</hi> 3.1, 2. <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.4, 14.</p>
            <p>Next, Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> comes to diſtinguiſhing Characters, <hi>p.</hi> 26, 27. Firſt <hi>Omniſciency:</hi> his Diſciples ſay, <hi>Thou knoweſt all things.</hi> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, I remember the Woman of <hi>Tekoah</hi> told <hi>David,</hi> that he was as an Angel of God, to know all things that were done in the Earth; and yet <hi>David</hi> was not God. Alſo the Angel that appeared to <hi>Abraham</hi> could tell <hi>Sarah</hi> that ſhe laugh'd, tho ſhe laugh'd but in her mind. Likewiſe the Prophet could tell <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi>'s Wife who ſhe was, and why ſhe came, e're he ſaw her. And on the other ſide, Chriſt expreſly ſaith, that the Father ſhews him all things; and that Revelation which <hi>John</hi> had of Chriſt, Chriſt had and received firſt of his Father, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.1. And yet he ſays that he knew not the day of Judgment.</p>
            <p>Next Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> urges his <hi>Omnipreſence;</hi> Chriſt would be with his Diſciples to the end of the World. But doth not <hi>Paul</hi> tell the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> Col. 2.5. <hi>That tho he was abſent in the Fleſh, yet he was preſent in the Spirit, joying and beholding their Order?</hi> yet <hi>Paul</hi> was not God.</p>
            <p>Next Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> urges his <hi>Omnipotency;</hi> he had all Power. But doth not Chriſt ſay, that all Power was given him? which could not be as he was God; for God moſt High can have no Power given him. And, Secondly, the Son ſaith expreſly, <hi>John</hi> 5.30. <hi>I can of my ſelf do nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> urges his <hi>Immortality.</hi> But it is ſaid of a Man (viz. <hi>Melchiſedec</hi>) that he was without beginning of Days or end of Life, and abideth for ever. Moreover, the Text Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> cites may mean God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. A larger Anſwer may be given hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, if God permit; at preſent let this
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:96824:22"/> ſuffice to theſe Inſtances.</p>
            <p>And whereas Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> urges, pag. 29. <hi>The Works that Chriſt did.</hi> I confeſs this had been a good Argument, had not Chriſt done it in his Father's Name and Power, and affirmed, that of himſelf he could do nothing; and when he raiſes <hi>Lazarus,</hi> he prays to his Father to ſhew whence the power came.</p>
            <p>Next Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> urges that Chriſt was <hi>one</hi> with the Father. But doth not Chriſt pray, John 17.22. <hi>That his Diſciples may be one, as he and his Father are one?</hi> which Oneneſs of Chriſt's Diſciples cannot be ſuppoſed to be meant of Eſſence; for Chriſt's true Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples are no more one in Eſſence after Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion than they were before.</p>
            <p>As to what Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> ſaith from pag. 33, to 38. concerning worſhipping Chriſt; for anſwer, the Reader may obſerve what I have ſaid concerning worſhipping Chriſt in the firſt part of this Book, where I think I have ſhewn that the whole Divine Eſſence is to be worſhipped as ſubſiſting in the Perſon of the Father, and that Divine Worſhip (I mean the higheſt Adoration) is not to be given to the Perſons of the Trinity diſtinct from one another; for that cannot be done without making three or four diſtinct Objects of our higheſt Adoration, which ought not to be. I have alſo ſhewn that the Worſhip due to Chriſt is as he is Mediator, and the immediate Repreſentative of God to us; and that we are to worſhip him as one that hath received Power from another, <hi>John</hi> 5.23. And this Worſhip is to be given to him as he is a Man; for it was the Manhood that was exalted; <hi>That at the Name of Jeſus every Knee ſhould bow.</hi> And it is very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable that the Worſhip we are to pay to Chriſt is in honour of another, to wit the Father, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.10, 11. <hi>every Knee is to bow to him, and every Tongue confeſs that Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt is Lord, to the Glory of God the Father.</hi> Every Tongue ſpeaking to the Judg confeſſeth that he is Lord, to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the King his Maſter. From the forecited place I argue:</p>
            <p>He that receives Worſhip and Honour, in honour, and to the glory of another, is not himſelf worſhipped as the ſupream Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and higheſt Power. But Jeſus Chriſt receives Worſhip and Honour, in honour, and to the glory of another; therefore he himſelf is not worſhipped as the ſupream Being and higheſt Power.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi> urges, <hi>page</hi> 39. <hi>That thoſe Scriptures of the Old Teſtament that are applicable to none but the moſt High God, are aſcribed to him, viz.</hi> to Chriſt. That is (as I take his meaning) ſome Scriptures that ſpeak of God in the Old Teſtament are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied unto Chriſt in the New; and ſo he gives divers Inſtances. I did deſign to have given a particular Reply to each of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances; but becauſe I have exceeded my Bounds already, I ſhall content my ſelf at preſent with ſome Replies in general.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I obſerve he cites ſome Texts in the New Teſtament, and applies them to Chriſt, which ſpeak only of God the Father.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Scripture is not altogether without Inſtances, that ſometimes that which in a ſtrict and moſt proper ſenſe belongs only to God moſt High, yet hath in ſome ſenſe been applied to Creatures, and to that which was not his Eſſence. It is proper only to the Eſſence of God to cauſe man to die with the ſight of it. <hi>No man,</hi> ſays God, <hi>can ſee my Face and live:</hi> Yet when <hi>Jacob</hi> wreſtled with the Angel, <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.30. he ſeems to attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute this Property to the Angel, looking on it a great wonder that his Life was preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; ſays he, <hi>I have ſeen God face to face, and my Life is preſerved.</hi> He whom <hi>Jacob</hi> here calls God, is called an Angel. In <hi>Hoſea</hi> 12.4. he is called <hi>the Lord God of Hoſts, the Lord is his Memorial.</hi> And the Angel that appears in the Buſh to <hi>Moſes,</hi> takes to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the incommunicable Names and Work of the moſt High.</p>
            <p>And if the applying ſome Scriptures in the Old Teſtament, ſpeaking of God, to Chriſt in the New Teſtament, be an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to prove him to be God; at that rate of reaſoning I can prove Chriſt to be <hi>David,</hi> and to be all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>John the Baptiſt</hi> to be <hi>Elias;</hi> becauſe <hi>David,</hi> ſpeaking of himſelf in the 22d Pſalm, ſays, ver. 18. <hi>They parted my Garments amongſt them, and caſt Lots upon my Veſture:</hi> And likewiſe of himſelf, Pſal.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:96824:23"/> 69. ſays, <hi>They gave me alſo Gall for my Meat, and in my thirſt they gave me Vinegar to drink.</hi> Now theſe Texts in the New Teſtament, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.34, 35. are expreſly applied to Chriſt: Is Chriſt therefore <hi>David?</hi> Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it is ſaid, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 11.1. <hi>When</hi> Iſrael <hi>was a Child, then I lov'd him, and called my Son out of</hi> Egypt: and this is applied to Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.15. Is Chriſt therefore all <hi>Iſrael?</hi> And becauſe the Lord ſays, Mal. 4.5. <hi>Behold, I will ſend you</hi> Elijah <hi>the Prophet;</hi> which is expreſly applied to <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.14. and <hi>Luke</hi> 1.17. will it therefore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly prove <hi>John</hi> to be <hi>Elias?</hi> Many would look upon this to be ſtrange and abſurd ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing.</p>
            <p>As to Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi>'s laſt three Reaſons, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I haſte to have done; and becauſe I think when what I have wrote is conſidered, they will do neither good nor hurt to our Cauſe; I will therefore wholly omit them.</p>
            <p>In what I have ſaid as a Reply to Mr. <hi>Taylor</hi>'s Endeavours to prove that Chriſt is of the Eſſence of God, I would not be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood as denying the thing, neither did I ever deny it: but my Deſign is to ſhew him and others, that if he intends to prove this point, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e muſt raiſe his Arguments to a higher pitch, or add new ones, becauſe theſe are too obſcure and weak to do it.</p>
            <p>Tho in the main I profeſs my ſelf ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox, yet if in any place I have dropt any ſuch Expreſſions as may be judged novel, I hope the candid Reader will conſider that the Controverſy is deep, and variouſly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood and explained by the moſt learned of our Party, as hath been hinted, namely, Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> Dr. <hi>Wallis,</hi> Dr. <hi>S—th,</hi> Mr. <hi>Monck,</hi> and others; who do all of them, in ſome conſiderable point or other, differ from each other about theſe things: 'Tis therefore no wonder if in ſome point or other I ſhould not agree with all of them.</p>
            <p>And if at unawares I ſhall or have advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced any Expreſſion contrary to ſound Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, upon information and conviction I ſhall be ready to ſign a Recantation. And if after this Apology, any body ſhall in any kind maliciouſly perſecute me, I think I ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with more honour than my Proſecutor can proſecute me.</p>
            <p>The Author hereof having much to do, and labouring under ſeveral Infirmities, and troubles of Mind, deſires the Prayers of ſuch as may receive any advantage by his Labours.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
